<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mysterie of redemption. Or The particular manner how man is redeemed from sinne, iustified before God, and made partaker of euerlasting life Describing the nature, causes, parts, properties and effects of iustification. With divers sweet and comfortable prayers interposed betweene euerie chapter.</title>
            <title>Mysterie of redemption.</title>
            <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 126 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20147.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106362</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842080</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6704</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6704)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 738:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mysterie of redemption. Or The particular manner how man is redeemed from sinne, iustified before God, and made partaker of euerlasting life Describing the nature, causes, parts, properties and effects of iustification. With divers sweet and comfortable prayers interposed betweene euerie chapter.</title>
                  <title>Mysterie of redemption.</title>
                  <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 228 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for VVilliam Cotton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Gabriel Powel.</note>
                  <note>Title page in read and black.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20147a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:1"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERIE OF Redemption.</p>
            <p>OR THE PARTICVLAR <hi>manner how Man is Redeemed</hi> from Sinne, Iuſtified before <hi>God, and made partaker of</hi> euerlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>DESCRIBING THE <hi>Nature, Cauſes, Parts, Properties</hi> and Effects of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>WITH DIVERS SWEET AND <hi>comfortable Prayers interpoſed</hi> betweene euerie Chapter.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>VVilliam Cotton.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, MY euer-honored Mother M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ELIZABETH POVVEL, <hi>all Prosperitie and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines externall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all point of the duty of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren towards their Parents, as in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence by ſeruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble offices, ſo in ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence
<pb facs="tcp:6704:3"/>by other effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual ſignifications, to yeeld proofe of their tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful minds: which neither any Child can omitte, without touch of ingratitude; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Parent forbeare, vvithout iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. Wherefore (moſt louing and deare Mother) leſt I ſhould ſeeme to neglect the roote, out of which I bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
<pb facs="tcp:6704:3"/>to forget the ſecondary Auctor of my being, or not to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber her, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I owe my ſelfe; after a long purſuite in a painfull chace, I now returne you ſuch a pray, as you were wont to loue, deſiring therby, to procure your Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. You are not ignorant, that theſe many yeares paſt I haue ſtudied and
<pb facs="tcp:6704:4"/>practiſed ſpirituall Phyſicke, trauelling in the Scrutinie of the maladies &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines incident &amp; proper to Soules: &amp; heere I offer vnto you a preſent of my profeſſion. I haue prepared abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the bread of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, for the repaſt of your Soule, that your kindneſſe in ſome part my bee counteruailed, and
<pb facs="tcp:6704:4"/>my dutie in ſome ſort not left vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Hitherto I haue principallie labored for others: but who hath more intereſtin the grape, then ſhee that plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the vine? &amp; who more right vnto the crop, then ſhee that ſowed the corne? Deſpiſe not the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of my years, neither deeme that God meaſureth his
<pb facs="tcp:6704:5"/>indowments by nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of daies. Hoarie ſenſes are ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnder greene lockes; &amp; ſome are riper in the Spring, then others in the Autumne of their age: a litle cloud may caſt a large ſhowre, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times GOD reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that to Babes, which he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealeth from the VViſeſt: which I alleage not
<pb facs="tcp:6704:5"/>to clayme any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the rate of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all habilities, but to auoide all touch of preſumption, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing my Elders. You haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſanguinity; but in ſpiritual alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, wee are of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall proximitie to our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And hee may bee a Father to the
<pb facs="tcp:6704:6"/>Soule, that is a Son to the Body, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the benefit of his temporarie life, by teaching his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent how to eſchew eternall death. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I ſpeak this, as if I were ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you were alreadie impathed in your voiage towards the Celeſtiall Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, the firſt ſteps wherunto your ſelf taught me, but that
<pb facs="tcp:6704:6"/>there may be ſome rubbes in the way, which I happily, by reaſon of my more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſearch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, being a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Guid, may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deſcry, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſhonour to your age, or diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, giue you war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to auoid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus, dear Mother, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending vnto you my moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:6704:7"/>duty, and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly deſiring that my ſincere affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may finde excuſe of my boldnes, I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> LONDON-HOVSE, <date>
                     <hi>this 18. day of Nouember, 1606.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most obedient and affectionate Sonne,</hi> Gabriel Powel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:7"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> Jf thou doest ſeriouſlie deſire, to learne the Mystery of thy Redemption, to vnderstand the holy Scriptures, to bee cleanſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſins, to bee filled with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:6704:8"/>to bee enriched with vertues, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne thy ſelfe in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, to be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in aduerſitie, to triumph ouer thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, to be enflamed in meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to dye happily, and to liue eternally: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thy ſelfe in this ſmall Manuall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the direct way vnto Heauen plainly diſcouered, the paſſage
<pb facs="tcp:6704:8"/>euidently cleared, the lets perfectly remoued, and the Trauailer exceedingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:9"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A <hi>Praier for Grace and Wiſedome, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Mystery of our Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. pag.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>CHAP. I. What Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is. pag. 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Confeſsion of Sinnes with Prayer for Remiſsion. pag.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and order of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is handled of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. pag. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Sinners Reſignation of himſelfe into the
<pb facs="tcp:6704:9"/>hands of his Redeemer. pag.</hi> 42</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. Of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Iuſtification; and firſt, of the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cauſe. pag. 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for Faith. p.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. Of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Cauſe of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. pag. 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for liuely ſenſe and aſſurance of our Iustification. pag.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. Of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe of our Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. pag. 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankeſgiuing for our Iustification intermixt with Confeſsion and Prayer. pag.</hi> 106</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6704:10"/>
               <item>CHAP. VI. Of the Finall Cauſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. pag. 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for eternall life. pag.</hi> 114</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. Of the Parts of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. pag. 120</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A patheticall Prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the temptations of Satan. pag.</hi> 152</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. Of the Properties of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. pag. 157</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer for Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. pag.</hi> 173</item>
               <item>CHAP. IX. Of the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Iuſtification. pag. 180</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Thankeſgiuing for our
<pb facs="tcp:6704:10"/>Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyned with Prayer. pag.</hi> 193</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Morning Prayer for a priuate Familie. p.</hi> 204</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Euening Prayer for a priuate Familie. p.</hi> 212</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Prayer to be ſaid for a Sicke-man, or by the Sicke-man himſelfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering but only the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. pag.</hi> 221</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6704:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6704:11"/>
            <head>THE MYSTERY of Redemption.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing all men by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are ſinners, <hi>(Rom. 3.24.)</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the glorie of God, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temporall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death: how may we eſcape this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6704:12"/>fearefull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Judgement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANSVVERE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee cannot eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt vs for our ſinnes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we bee recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto him and iuſtified in his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which that wee may the better apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and attaine vnto; it is neceſſarie that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6704:12"/>we conſider both the Nature and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Iuſtification, and alſo the meanes and manner how it is wrought in vs.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A PRAYER FOR Grace and Wiſedome to <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the Mysterie of our Redemption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALmighty and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, and in Chriſt Ieſus our moſt gracious and mercifull Father, I thy poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, miſerable &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner, do humbly proſtrate my ſelf before the heauenly throne of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6704:13"/>thy diuine Maieſtie, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely beſeeching thy Fatherly goodnes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly to graunt vnto me thy heauenly grace and wiſedome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may truly learne to know thee rightly, and be diligent to performe all thy precepts effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Enlarge my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and encreaſe my knowledge. Giue me a liuely ſenſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne ſweete fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſowre and ſowre from ſweete, good from euill and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from good, that ſin and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceiue me not vnder the cloak
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6704:13"/>of Religion and vertue. O Lord, this muſt bee thy worke; for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that my reaſon is blind, by will is fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, my wit craftie to deceiue my ſelfe, my vnderſtanding and all my naturall powers, quite alienated and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged from thee. But, good Father, diſpell thou theſe cloudes and confuſions of peruerſe ignorance, and endue me with thy holy Spirit of grace and wiſedome, that I may haue my hart cleanſed from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections of this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6704:14"/>deceitful world, and the eyes of my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding opened, to ſee and embrace thine euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting truth, eſpecially the admirable Myſterie of our Redemption by the obedience and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy deere Sonne our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Endue me O Lord, with the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this heauenlie knowledge, and let me be able to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene truth and error, that I may bee alwaies free from hereſie, and not be entangled with falſe doctrine, nor defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6704:14"/>with the loathſome pitch of mans inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but that I may ſafely walke the right way into thy kingdom, and faithfully apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and take hold of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and righteouſnes of thy Sonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſo that my whole life and conuerſation may bee hereafter dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the honour and glorie of thy name, and peace of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, through Chriſt our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mediator and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate; in whoſe name I farther pray vnto thee as himſelfe hath taught
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6704:15"/>me, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>What Iuſtification is. <hi>CHAP. I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole courſe &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our ſaluation is abſolued, as it were, in two degrees, 1. In the <hi>knowledge of our owne mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</hi> 2. In <hi>confidence of the Diuine mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note>2 Of our miſerie there are three partes, 1. The <hi>Faulte.</hi> 2. The <hi>Guilte.</hi> 3. The <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Diuine mercie three-fold.</note>3 Of the Diuine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6704:15"/>Mercy there are three partes in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, oppoſitive vnto theſe 1. <hi>Remiſsion of the fault.</hi> 2. <hi>Abſolution from the guilte.</hi> 3. <hi>Deliuerance from the puniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe from our miſerie, vnto the Diuine mercy is termed <hi>Iustification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Iuſtification is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken two waies,<note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> 1. <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> or Naturally. 2. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litically</hi> or Iudicially.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Iustification Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> or Naturally <hi>taken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phyſicall.</note> ſignifieth an actual tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation or change fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inherent qualitie of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6704:16"/>vnto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent qualitie of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes; from euill to good.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Thus muſt that place (<hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.11.) be vnderſtood, <hi>Hee that is righteous, let him be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 And certainely a man is denominated righteous, from inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t righteouſnes, (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.17.) <hi>He that doth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, is righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 Iuſtification being taken in this fenſe, is indeede <hi>Iachoatiue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification,</hi> or <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is a certaine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6704:16"/>change betweene inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent contrary termes or qualities.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Iustification Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically</hi> or Iudicially <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Politicall.</hi>
                  </note> ſignifieth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of a ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Abſolution or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vpon a man, by ſome Iudge out of a tribunall or Iudgement ſeate. (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.) <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? It is God that iustifieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 And this ſenſe is common, both to ſuch as haue <hi>Inherent proper righteouſnes,</hi> and alſo to ſuch as be not ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6704:17"/>but haue the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of another</hi> appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto them.</p>
               <p n="12">12 For hee that is Righteous in himſelfe, may by a Iudge be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced ſo to bee, by his own inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</p>
               <p n="13">13 So are the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Angels iuſtified by God.</p>
               <p n="14">14 So alſo ſhould Man haue bin iuſtified, if hee had continued in his originall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Alſo, a man may be ſaid to be iuſtified, that is, pronounced iuſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6704:17"/>or righteous, by that righteouſnes which is not inherent in himſelf, but is properly another Mans, but made his by couenant.</p>
               <p n="16">16 After this manner any Debter may be ſaid to bee iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of his ſurety, who in his name ſatisfieth the creditour and payeth the debt.</p>
               <p n="17">17 And in this ſenſe only, is Iuſtification v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the argument we haue to treate of, which is thus defined.</p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>Iustification</hi> is the Sentence of GOD,<note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6704:18"/>as iudge in his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall ſeate, whereby for the ſatisfaction and obedience of Chriſt he freely remitteth the ſins of the beleeuing-ſinner and imputeth the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt vnto him, for his glorie, and the ſinners euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <note place="margin">That Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is a iudiciall Act.</note>19 Now that Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is a iudicial act, it is manifeſt by ſundrie reaſons.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>I.</hi> Becauſe it is plainely deſcribed ſo in Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.2.3.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>II.</hi> Becauſe in this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6704:18"/>Act there are, Debt, that is, Sin, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12.) a law accuſing, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19.20.) conſcience wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.) an Aduocate pleading, (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.) and a finall Sentence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.24.25.28.</p>
               <p n="22">22 <hi>III.</hi> Becauſe ſuch words as be equiualent vnto Iuſtification, are iudicial, as to remit ſins, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7.) to looſe ſins, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18.) to forgiue, (<hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.13.) not to impute ſinnes, (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.) to put out the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6704:19"/>hand-writing, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>IV.</hi> Becauſe the words which are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite vnto Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are Iudicial, as Accuſation, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.) Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 12.37. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34.) Binding, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18.) Retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſins, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Euen as the word <hi>Iustification,</hi> ſo is the worde <hi>Imputation</hi> alſo common:<note place="margin">Of Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> For Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is ſaid to bee IMPVTED, both vnto him who is inherently iuſt in himſelfe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto him that hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6704:19"/>not his owne inherent, but the righteouſneſſe of another, namelie Chriſts righteouſneſſe applied vnto him.</p>
               <p n="25">25 That <hi>Iuſtification</hi> is common, appeareth by that ſpeech of the Apoſtle, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.) where hee ſaith, that Man is iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>not by the works of the Law, but by faith in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26 Whereby he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declareth, that a man may bee iuſtified, that is, pronounced iuſt and righteous, aſwel by his own works or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6704:20"/>of the Law (if any had ſuch works in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) as a man may by faith, that is, by the righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith.</p>
               <p n="27">27 So alſo that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> is common, it is euident out of theſe words of the Apoſtle, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.) <hi>To him that worketh the wages is not imputed by fauour, but by debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28 In which words hee ſheweth, that the righteouſnes of works, that is inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, may be ſaid to be imputed to a man (if
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6704:20"/>any were ſo well quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) as well as the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of faith.</p>
               <p n="29">29 But our ſpeech is of the Imputation of anothers righteouſnes.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>CONFESSION OF ſinnes, with prayer for <hi>Remiſſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Haue ſinned, ô Lord, I haue ſinned. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and euer-crying guilte of my ſins conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually calles for infinite and neuer dying pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Oh, I haue ſinned, and therefore am aſhamed to appeare before thee, much more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6704:21"/>to craue any good thing at thy hands. I am a weake and wretched creature, and thou art a GOD of infinite power and Maieſtie. I am a guilty and grieuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour, thou a moſt iuſt and ſeuere Iudge. Sin hath left no good thing in me, al is woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, al is poyſoned, and how ſhall I appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, into whoſe preſence ſhall enter no vncleane thing. Alas! I am ſicke with ſin. Sicke? yea dead; twice dead, ſubiect to mortalitie, &amp; ſubiect to eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6704:21"/>I was conceiued and borne in ſinne, and hitherto haue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally liued therein; the greatnes of my diſeaſe hath almoſt quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed the ſenſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and my continuall cuſtome in ſinning co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth my impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and taketh from me the opinion of ſin. But now the only glimpſe of felicity cauſeth me to acknowledge my owne miſerie, therefore I am conſtrained to confeſſe with <hi>Dauid, I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned grieuouſly,</hi> and there ſtop, becauſe I cannot
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6704:22"/>recken them. My heart is the roote and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of corruption, my eyes the eyes of vanity, my eares the eares of folly, my mouth the mouth of deceipt, my hands the hands of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and euery part of my body doth diſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor thee, which thou haſt created for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and would be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of thee. My vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding apprehendeth nothing but ſinne, my will affecteth nothing but wickedneſſe, my memory retaineth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but euill things.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6704:22"/>As for thy holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and heauenly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, O Lord, ſo farre haue I been from obſeruing or keeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parte thereof as I ought, that I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded tranſgreſſion vnto blindnes, malice to ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and rebellion to ſin. What now ſhall I ſay? To whom ſhall I go? or whither ſhall I flie? Oh, I ſinke in ſin. O Death! O Graue! Yours is the victorie. Thou ſeeſt, O Lord, what I haue been from the beginning, &amp; what now I am. Neither doe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6704:23"/>I maruell ſo much at my wickednes, as I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire thy goodnes, that thou haſt ſuffered mee, with vnſpeakeable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, thus long to run on in my ſins. Becauſe thou art ſo good, I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined I might be ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Becauſe thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt beſtow ſuch great benefits vpon mee, I thought I might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo great offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. So that the ſame medicine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt ordained againſt ſin, I haue made a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation vnto ſin. Who but thou would ſuffer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6704:23"/>theſe contempts, and yet be contemned ſtill? Notwithſtanding, O moſt gracious Father, ſeeing thou haſt ſworne thou deſireſt not the death of a penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, if I repent, wilt not thou be pleaſed? if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto thee, wilt thou be offended? No, no, I know thou doſt long vntill I come vnto thee. Why then, moſt mercifull Sauiour, I come, I come quickely. Reiect not thy poore creature, that deiecteth himſelfe and wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeth vpon thee. If I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6704:24"/>come ful of ſcabbes and woundes, thou canſt heale me againe. If I be blind, thou canſt reſtore me to my ſight againe. If I be dead, thou canſt raiſe me vp again. Thou ſhalt ſprinckle mee, O Lord, with Iſope, and I ſhall bee cleane; thou ſhalt waſh me, &amp; I ſhall bee whiter then ſnow. Thy mercies are greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine offences. Thy pitie is more then mine iniquitie: and thou art able to pardon more ſinnes then I am able to commit. If thou refuſe me, who ſhall receaue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6704:24"/>and comfort mee? If thou forſake me, who ſhall embrace and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me? Heere I am, do with me as ſeemeth good in thy eies. If thou wilt, I ſhall ſee thy face and reioice: if thou wilt perſecute mee, glorifie thy ſelfe. But wilt thou enter into iudgement with thy ſeruant? thou art iuſt to all. But wilt thou bee extreame to marke what is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe? Lord, who may abide it? But wilt thou bee terrible vnto mee? Where then is thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? Haue mercy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6704:25"/>vpon mee, whoſe propertie is alwaies to haue mercie; haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon me, O Father, neither looke vnto the multitude of my ſinnes, but vnto the multitude of thy mercies, for thy only Son Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with thee &amp; the holy Ghoſt, bee all honor and glory, both now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6704:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The manner and order of Iuſtification, where alſo is handled of vocation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow in this Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of Man, wherby he is pronounced righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, by the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of another, to wit, of Chriſt, God procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this maner and order.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Firſt, there is an <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Vocation,</hi> or <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> wherby God offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Chriſt &amp; his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and the ſinner apprehendeth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6704:26"/>offered by faith.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Effectuall Calling what it is.</note>3 <hi>Effectuall Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or <hi>Calling,</hi> is that whereby God calleth out of darkeneſſe into light, from the power of Satan vnto God in Chriſt Ieſus, thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he elected of his meere grace, by the promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the couenant of grace, or preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>Called</hi> alſo, by the ſame grace of God, anſwere and beleeue in him through Ieſus Chriſt. This anſwere is of Faith, which indeed is the condition of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6704:26"/>promiſe in the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Effectuall Calling hath two parts. 1 Outward calling.</note>5 Wherefore our Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall calling conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of two parts. 1. The <hi>Outward calling</hi> of ſuch as be elect by the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Couenant vnder the condition of faith, and that of Gods meere grace.<note place="margin">2. Inward faith.</note> 2. <hi>Inward Faith</hi> wrought in them by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame grace, which is nothing elſe but the fulfilling of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">Note wel.</note>6 The former grace may bee termed the <hi>Grace of vocation,</hi> and is common to all that are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6704:27"/>called, Elect and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The latter grace may be called, the <hi>Grace of faith,</hi> appertaining only to the Elect.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">A two-fold appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in effectuall calling.</note>8 So then in Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Calling there is a two-fold application: the one of GOD, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſt &amp; his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes: the other of a ſinner, apprehending Chriſt being offered by faith, and applying him vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="9">9 If it bee demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether the will of man in his calling or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion be meerely paſsiue,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6704:27"/>or actiue alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">Anſwere. How the will of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth in his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>10 I anſwere: <hi>In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the grace of God</hi> which preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth man, the will (ſeeing it is not yet begun to bee rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate) is <hi>meerely Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue:</hi> as may be proued.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>I.</hi> Becauſe al Mans ſtrength &amp; abilitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpirituall and heauenly things is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exſtinct, ſo as he can neither prepare himſelfe to grace, nor receiue it being offered, nor turne vnto God, nor will, deſire or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after that which is good &amp; acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6704:28"/>to God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.21.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>II.</hi> Becauſe we are all dead in ſinne (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loſſ.</hi> 3.12.) but a dead man is only paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue in reſpect of his quickening.</p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>III.</hi> Becauſe the will is not only dead, but alſo ſtubborne of it ſelfe, and cannot chuſe but reſiſt, being not moued and kindled by God. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 But <hi>In reſpect of the Time</hi> in which the conuerſion is wrought,<note place="margin">Note.</note> the will is not like a ſtocke, but whileſt it is healed and cured by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6704:28"/>God, it is <hi>Actiue,</hi> that is, it is not idle and void of all ſenſe and motion, but followeth the holy Ghoſt who draweth it.</p>
               <p n="15">15 For in the very act of Conuerſion or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God cauſeth vs by grace to wil, he moueth and inclineth our wills, but yet ſo as the whole efficacy of the action dependeth vpon Gods ſpirit (<hi>Philip.</hi> 2.13.) <hi>It is God who worketh in vs both the will and the deed:</hi> where <hi>Will</hi> is not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the ſubſtance of the will, but of a new qualitie.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:6704:29"/>
               <p n="16">
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall calling.</note>16 After this effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall Calling follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God imputeth that righteouſnes of Chriſt, being apprehended by faith in Vocation, vnto the ſinner, as if it were his owne proper righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes. Or, whereby hee pronounceth him iuſt in that righteouſnes of Chriſt, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner receiueth it being imputed vnto him by God.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <note place="margin">A two-fold Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>17 In Iuſtification likewiſe there is a two-fold application; the firſt is <hi>the Imputation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6704:29"/>of GOD;</hi> the ſecond is <hi>the ſinners apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and application by faith, of that other righteouſnes being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by God vnto him.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Theſe two ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications which are in Iuſtification, doe differ from thoſe two which were in effectuall Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or Vocation.</p>
               <p n="19">19 For in Vocation, the application of God is called <hi>Oblation,</hi> or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie <hi>Calling:</hi> In Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation it is termed <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>II.</hi> In Vocation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6704:30"/>the application of Man is called, <hi>Apprehenſion of offered righteouſneſſe by faith;</hi> or, <hi>Faith in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered righteouſnes:</hi> In Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, it is termed <hi>Faith in imputed righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">
                  <note place="margin">A two-fold office of faith.</note>21 Hence wee muſt obſerue a twofold of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Faith: <hi>One</hi> in Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Calling, when it receiueth Chriſt with his righteouſnes being offered: the <hi>Other</hi> in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth Chriſt and his righteouſnes being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto him.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Wee muſt alſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6704:30"/>note, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid, <hi>Man is iuſtified by faith,</hi> that <hi>Faith is</hi> meant which went before in Effectual calling;<note place="margin">Note.</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which apprehendeth Chriſt and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes being offered.</p>
               <p n="23">23 As for that <hi>Faith</hi> in Iuſtification, which apprehendeth the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted righteouſnes of Chriſt, by it wee are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid to bee ſaued, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtified. (<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.) <hi>By grace you are ſaued through faith.</hi> Eternall ſaluation followeth Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</p>
               <p n="24">24 If it be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6704:31"/>
                  <hi>Whether when the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is apprehended by faith in Effectuall Calling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>a man may be ſaid to be iuſtified by that righteouſnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25 I anſwere.<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Not ſo: For Iuſtification is the pronunciation of a Sentence: In Vocation there is no Sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; wherefore a man cannot be iuſtified by ſole Vocation.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Againe,<note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> if any will aske: <hi>Whether ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is by faith in him that is called, a man may not be denominated righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6704:31"/>by that righteouſnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27 I anſwere.<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> I will not plainly deny this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort: namely, that he is righteous by faith; but that he may bee ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and called righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I would not ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme: ſeeing the Iudge hath not yet pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſentence vpon him; to wit, that Sentence that is of a certaine new grace.</p>
               <p n="28">28 For it is not but by grace that ſuch as are iuſt by faith in effectual calling, God pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them ſo to be, and imputeth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6704:32"/>of another vnto them, as if it were their owne.</p>
               <p n="29">29 And thus much for the order whereby God proceedeth in the Iuſtification of a ſinner.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>THE SINNERS RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of himſelfe into <hi>the hands of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Lord God, which art the higheſt and the loweſt, the fartheſt off and the neereſt to, the longeſt angrie and the ſooneſt pleaſed: wherefore ſhould I bee affraid to ſpeake vnto thee? Thou haſt made
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6704:32"/>all things for mee, and me for thy ſelfe. Thou haſt giuen me al things, that I ſhould giue my ſelfe wholy vnto thee; But I haue taken the commoditie of all thy benefits, and yet I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer gaue thee the glory and tribute, which of duty I was bound to giue thee. Thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were alwaies obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient at my commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, becauſe thou haddeſt giuen them ſo in charge; and I alwaies atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to offend thee, for whoſe ſake each thing was readie to do
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6704:33"/>me ſeruice. Thou haſt giuen me health, but ſin and rebellion was the fruit thereof. Thou haſt giuen me ſtrength, but I haue employed it in the ſeruice of thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Notwithſtanding all which, thou haſt ſtill ſought by all meanes to draw mee vnto thee. Thou haſt looked and tarried for my conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and I haue abuſed thy patience. Thou haſt called mee, and I haue ſtopped my eares at thy calling. Thou haſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mee a long time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and I haue conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6704:33"/>it in vanity &amp; far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion. Thou haſt ſtricken me, and I haue not felt it. Thou haſt corrected me, and I would not receaue thy correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea the more I haue been chaſtiſed &amp; cheriſhed by thee, the more hath mine heart bin hardened, ſhewing my ſelfe vnthankful for the one, and rebellious towards the other. Yet for all this, O moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and louing Father, ſithence thou haſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been ſo gracious vnto me, and baſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded me that I ſhould
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6704:34"/>neuer deſpaire, nor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt thy goodneſſe: I therfore referre my ſelf wholy to thy mercy, &amp; doe beſeech thee to graunt mee grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my life, that from this time forwards I may euer pleaſe thee, and ſerue thee in ſuch ſort, that I neuer ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate my ſelfe from thee any more, but may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually remaine in thy grace &amp; fauour world without end. O ſweete Sauiour, diddeſt not thou ſay, <hi>Draw neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, &amp; I will draw neere vnto you?</hi> I challenge my
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6704:34"/>Lord. Beare witneſſe with me, ô yee heauen and earth, and all yee bleſſed Angels, &amp; thou holy of Holies, the holy Ghoſt, beare witneſſe with me in this houre, that I giue my ſelf who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto my Redeemer. Take me ſweet IESVS vnto thee, and giue me not ouer vnto my ſelfe againe. I am thine, not mine, temper mee as thou wouldeſt haue me. I am thy Image, I will bee like thee. Oh, that my waies were ſo directed, that I might keep thy ſtatutes! what
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6704:35"/>pleaſure is it for mee, to walke in darkeneſſe? Trie mee O Lord, and ſearch my heart, if there be any way of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in me; and leade me home, and I wil follow my Lord whither ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Cauſes of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and firſt, of the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Cauſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſes of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diuerſly conſidered.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He CAVSES of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered diuerſly, to wit, as Iuſtification it ſelfe is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6704:35"/>taken, either <hi>Actiuely,</hi> in reſpect of God who iuſtifieth: or <hi>Paſsiuely,</hi> in reſpect of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is iuſtified.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">The effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe Actiuely taken.</note>2 The EFFICIENT <hi>cauſe</hi> of Iuſtification, as it is <hi>Actiuely</hi> taken, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Principall,</hi> or <hi>Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall</hi> effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note>3 The <hi>Principall Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,</hi> is GOD (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.) the <hi>Father,</hi> in the <hi>Sonne,</hi> by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19) The Father Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the Son Obſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the Holie Ghoſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummant. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:6704:36"/>
               <p n="4">4 For it is his part to abſolue from guilt, by whoſe iuſtice a man is made guiltie. It is hee that pronounceth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> righteous, whoſe wil is the rule &amp; ſquare of all righteouſnes. And it is he that giueth Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life or death, who by nature, right and office is the ſupreme Iudge.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The <hi>Impellent cauſe</hi> of this Efficient, is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, <hi>Internall,</hi> or <hi>Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</note>6 The <hi>Internal cauſe,</hi> is the Grace or Mercie of the Father, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.) as well by reaſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6704:36"/>of the good pleaſure of his will in predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into the adoption of Sonnes (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5.) as alſo by reaſon of his oëconomie and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, both in ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Sonne for this end, and in applying vnto vs the benefit of Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p n="7">7 And this Grace (which in Scriptures is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; in Schooles, <hi>Gratia gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum faciens,</hi> and <hi>Gratis dans</hi>) is perpetually op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt Workes, (which are the gifts
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6704:37"/>of Grace, termed in Schooles <hi>Gratiae gratis datae</hi>) becauſe God took the firſt cauſe of our Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification not from vs or our workes, but in himſelf, and from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, according to the vnſearchable riches of the glory of his grace. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">No Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in vs to Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>8 Whereupon it is manifeſt, that there can bee no Diſpoſition of our ſelues or Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by vs to induce this forme of Iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="9">9 For albeit there are two principall degrees of Preparation that go
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6704:37"/>before Iuſtification, if not in time, yet in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to wit, the ſenſe of our owne <hi>Miſerie,</hi> and a confuſed knowledge of the <hi>Mercie</hi> of God; yet all this maketh nothing for the Efficient Cauſe, not only of condignity (as the Schoole-men ſpeake) but not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruence.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</note>10 The <hi>Externall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellent Cauſe</hi> of this Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient is Chriſt aſwell in reſpect <hi>of his Merite,</hi> as alſo <hi>of his Efficacie</hi> and operation.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>Of his Merite:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee acquired the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6704:38"/>benefit of Iuſtification vnto vs, both by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue and Paſſiue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; by his life and death. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>Of his Efficacie:</hi> Becauſe he applieth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually the acquired benefit of Iuſtification vnto vs, both by offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it in the preaching of his Word, and alſo by conferring the ſame by the inward effectual operation of his holie Spirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               <p n="13">13 But that we may more plainely declare,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6704:38"/>how God is the Effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe of our Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:<note place="margin">How God is ſaid to Iuſtifie.</note> wee muſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerue that the <hi>Maner of Effecting, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is ſaid to iuſtifie</hi> is diuerſe and ſundrie.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> By works.</note>14 <hi>I.</hi> God is ſaid to Iuſtifie <hi>by Works and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Righteouſnes.</hi> So he iuſtifieth the bleſſed Angels. So alſo hee ſhould haue Iuſtified Man, if he had not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. And thus the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites ſought Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the workes of the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31.32.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> By Faith.</note>15 <hi>II.</hi> God is ſaid to Iuſtifie <hi>of Faith,</hi> or <hi>by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6704:39"/>Faith.</hi> By <hi>Faith</hi> I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Chriſt &amp; his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, or Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or Obedience, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits being apprehended by Faith.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <note place="margin">Note wel.</note>16 In this manner of Iuſtifying are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended two things. 1. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the Merits of Chriſt. 2. Our <hi>Faith,</hi> without which the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt cannot be applied vnto vs effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for our Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="17">17 This Merite of Chriſt is the cauſe of all Spirituall bleſſings (in the execution of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Election) which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6704:39"/>God beſtoweth vpon vs; though after a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe manner.</p>
               <p n="18">18 I ſay, <hi>in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the decree of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The merit of Chriſt cannot be the cauſe of Election.</note> becauſe the Merit of Chriſt cannot be the cauſe of Election it ſelf, but onely Gods good pleaſure proceeding of his meere loue &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5. 1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.7.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               <p n="19">19 <hi>I.</hi> Becauſe the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Chriſt was not from all eternitie.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>II.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt himſelf, as he is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, was elected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:6704:40"/>before the foundation of the world. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.18. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>III.</hi> Becauſe the Merit of Chriſt is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our eternall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: for therefore Chriſt merited for vs, becauſe wee were Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But Chriſt may well bee ſaid to bee the <hi>Materiall Cauſe</hi> of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,<note place="margin">Note.</note> if wee take the matter for the <hi>Subiect,</hi> or <hi>Matter in which</hi> (<hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4.) <hi>He elected vs in him,</hi> that is, in Chriſt; for Chriſt is the head, in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6704:40"/>which is grounded the election of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <note place="margin">The merit of Chriſt the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of Vocation.</note> 23 To returne to our purpoſe. Chriſt and his merit, is the Efficient Cauſe of our <hi>Effectuall vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> or <hi>Calling,</hi> which is not from all eternitie, but in time; yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect vnto Faith; ſeeing Faith is but then giuen, and is the ſecond part of our calling.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <note place="margin">Of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note>24 Againe, Chriſt and his Merite is the cauſe of our <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> but not without Faith, wherewith in Effectual calling we haue appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6704:41"/>and laid hold on him.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <note place="margin">And of Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>25 Laſtly, Chriſt and his merit, is the cauſe of our <hi>Glorification;</hi> but with Faith apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the imputed righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt in Iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Hereby wee ſee that Man is Iuſtified by the Merits of Chriſt, as it were by a manner or way whereby God iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth him; but not without Faith appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that Merit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered in Effectuall Calling.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whereupon the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6704:41"/>Apoſtle vnto the <hi>Rom.</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> expreſſeth this manner (which is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thing) by the onely name of <hi>Faith,</hi> wherunto ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he ioyneth <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> as (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.) <hi>The righteouſnes of God by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> So (<hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.) <hi>Man is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.) <hi>Through Faith in his blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28 <hi>III.</hi> God is ſaid to iuſtifie <hi>by his Grace &amp; Mercy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. By grace.</note> And certainely this Grace doth excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well agree with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6704:42"/>Faith, but not at all with Workes. (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 2.8.9.) Theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe well agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>God iustifieth by Faith;</hi> and, <hi>God iustifieth by Grace:</hi> which cannot be affirmed of Workes.</p>
               <p n="29">29 But heere Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion may bee moued concerning the Order of theſe two.<note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Faith or Grace go before: Whether Faith bee the cauſe of Grace; or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, whether Grace bee the cauſe of Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">
                  <note place="margin">Anſwere. Faith go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before the grace of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>30 I Anſwere. Faith goeth before, &amp; Grace followeth after. Faith,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6704:42"/>that is, Chriſt and his merits being apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Faith in Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Calling, is the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by GOD iuſtifieth a man.</p>
               <p n="31">31 And to ſpeake more plainely hereof,<note place="margin">Note well.</note> All ſpirituall bleſſings in the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods decree of Election, as <hi>Vocation, Iuſtification and Glorification,</hi> do proceed from Gods Grace. For example;</p>
               <p n="32">32 In <hi>Effectuall Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> the firſt thing is the Merite of Chriſt, then followeth the Grace of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6704:43"/>GOD, after commeth Vocation.</p>
               <p n="33">33 So alſo in <hi>Iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> firſt is the Merite of Chriſt, which was apprehended in Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then there is the Grace of God, whereof proceedeth Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="34">34 And likewiſe in <hi>Glorification,</hi> the firſt is the Merit of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imputed in Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Faith, next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Grace of God, and then Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p n="35">35 Herein ſtands the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6704:43"/>difference, that in Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall Vocation or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the onely Merite of Chriſt without our faith, is the cauſe of Grace.</p>
               <p n="36">36 But in Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; Glorification the Merit of Chriſt being apprehended by Faith, is the cauſe of Grace.</p>
               <p n="37">37 Out of theſe things which wee haue ſaid, it is euident, that Faith, or Chriſt and his merit apprehended by faith, is the cauſe of that Grace whereby God iuſtifieth man.</p>
               <p n="38">38 Whereupon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6704:44"/>that the Apoſtle had ſaid (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.) <hi>Wee are iustified freely</hi> (that is) <hi>by his grace,</hi> preſently hee addeth, <hi>through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Christ Ieſus:</hi> noting thereby the cauſe of that Grace whereby we are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, namely the Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by faith in Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall calling.</p>
               <p n="39">39 And (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.) <hi>Therefore is the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by Faith, that it might come by Grace:</hi> in which words the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in mateth that life eternall is therefore of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6704:44"/>Faith, that there might bee place for Grace, which is the Effect of Faith apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the imputed righteouſnes of Chriſt in Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="40">40 If it bee deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>How the Merite of Christ and the Grace of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>which is contrary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to merit, may conſiſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">41 I Anſwere.<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> The Merite of Chriſt (not our owne merites) may wel ſtand together with the Grace of GOD. For Chriſts ſatisfaction wherby he ſatisfied the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6704:45"/>Iuſtice of his Father, is that thing that meriteth the Grace of God for vs.</p>
               <p n="42">42 But if you ſpeake of our owne merits, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certainely they cannot ſtand together with the Grace of God, but are quite contrarie vnto it.</p>
               <p n="43">
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi> Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient two fold.</note>43 The <hi>Organicall Efficient Cauſe</hi> of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is two-fold, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall</hi> or <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="44">44 The <hi>Instrumental Cauſe</hi> which exhibiteth the benefit of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall.</hi>
                  </note> is the <hi>Goſpell</hi> and <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> wherby
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6704:45"/>the benefits of Chriſt are offered, conferred and ſealed vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="45">45 The <hi>Goſpell</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Goſpell of Grace</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 20.24.) becauſe it declareth and offereth the Grace of God vnto vs: alſo, the <hi>Word of Grace</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 20.32.) the <hi>Word of Saluation</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 13.26) the <hi>Word of Life</hi> (<hi>Phil.</hi> 2.16.) And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, The Goſpell of Chriſt is <hi>the power of God vnto ſaluation to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that beleeueth. Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p n="46">46 Of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6704:46"/>ſanctifieth &amp; cleanſeth his Church by the waſhing of water through the Word.</hi> (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26.) Alſo, <hi>Hee ſaued vs by the waſhing of the new birth, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of the holy Ghost.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſaueth vs by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Ieſus Christ.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p n="47">47 And of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> Chriſt teſtifieth that we receiue his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which was giuen for vs (<hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.) &amp; drinke his blood, that is ſhed for many for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.27.28.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:6704:46"/>
               <p n="48">48 If it bee demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>How the Sacraments are instruments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="49">49 I Anſwere. The Sacraments conferre grace,<note place="margin">Anſwere. How the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts conferre Grace.</note> becauſe they are a meanes to giue and exhibite to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mind Chriſt with his benefits: and this they do by their ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p n="50">50 For they ſerue as a particular and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble certificate to aſſure ſuch as bee partakers thereof, of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſins and of euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:6704:47"/>
               <p n="51">51 Alſo, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre grace, as the Kings letters are ſaid to ſaue the life of a malefactor, when they doe but ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to him and others, that the Kings pleaſure is to ſhew fauour.</p>
               <p n="52">52 Againe, they may be ſaid to confer grace, becauſe they are a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or pledge of the Grace of GOD; and by this pledge Faith is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which is an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to apprehend or receiue grace.</p>
               <p n="53">53 A King ſaith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Subiects.<note place="margin">Note.</note> He that brings the head of ſuch
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6704:47"/>a Traytour ſhall haue a thouſand pounds. He that hath the head, may ſay, Heere is a thouſand pounds: becauſe it is vnto him a pledge vpon the Kings word of the receipt of ſo much.</p>
               <p n="54">54 Laſtly, the Word of God conferres grace (for it is the <hi>power of God vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that beleeue</hi>) which it doth by ſignifying the wil of God by the eare to the mind: Now euery Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is the Word of GOD made viſible to the eye: the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts therfore conferre grace
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6704:48"/>by vertue of their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and by reaſon they are a pledge by the appointment of GOD of his mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="55">55 If it be ſaid,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                  <hi>The Sacraments are not onlie ſignes and ſeales, but alſo inſtruments to conuey the grace of God to vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="56">56 I Anſwere:<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> The Sacraments are not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments hauing the grace of God tied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, or ſhut vp in them: but inſtruments to which grace is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by aſſiſtance in the right vſe thereof.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:6704:48"/>
               <p n="57">57 Becauſe in and with the right vſe of the Sacraments, God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres grace: and thus they are inſtruments &amp; no otherwiſe, that is, morall, not phyſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</p>
               <p n="58">58 The <hi>Administeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Cauſe</hi> of Iuſtification,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall.</hi>
                  </note> are aſwell the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Word (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23.) as alſo the <hi>Martyrs</hi> of Chriſt (<hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.) who by their teſtimony and example teach, that there is no righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which may conſiſt before the tribunall of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6704:49"/>GOD, but onely the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="59">59 And ſo much for the Efficient Cauſe of Iuſtification Actiuelie taken on Gods part.</p>
               <p n="60">
                  <note place="margin">The Effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe on Mans part is, Faith.</note>60 Now on Mans part, <hi>Iuſtification Paſsiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie taken,</hi> the Efficient cauſe of it is altogether <hi>Inſtrumentall:</hi> and this is <hi>Faith,</hi> by which (not for which) wee are ſaid to be iuſtified, aſwell in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Correlatiue</hi> thereof, as alſo of the <hi>Contrarie</hi> the Law and good workes.</p>
               <p n="61">61 <hi>In regard of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatiue,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:6704:49"/>to wit, Chriſt &amp; his Merits, becauſe the whole forme of Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith is ſited in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, not in the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or nature thereof; ſeeing wee are iuſtified by Faith, as it is relatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied vnto his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatiue.</p>
               <p n="62">62 <hi>In regard of the Contrarie,</hi> becauſe thoſe good workes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie vnto the Law, required in the perſon of a iuſtified Man, are worthily excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the merit and act of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</p>
               <p n="63">63 But to ſpeake
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6704:50"/>more plainely of this point.<note place="margin">Faith what it is.</note> Faith is a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent apprehenſion of the mercy of GOD through the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt in the promiſe of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="64">
                  <note place="margin">The parts of Faith.</note>64 The <hi>parts of Faith</hi> are three. 1. <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the mind and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. 2. <hi>Aſſent</hi> in the will. 3. <hi>Confidence</hi> in the heart.</p>
               <p n="65">65 Theſe three acts may be conſidered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly; ſeeing a man may know a thing and yet not aſſent thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp; beleeue the ſame to bee true, and yet not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6704:50"/>make it his own by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall application &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, which cannot conſiſt without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and aſſent.</p>
               <p n="66">66 Theſe three parts are excellently wel laid downe in the 14. chap. of S. <hi>Iohn. Beleeueſt thou that I am in the Father, and the Father is in mee?</hi> this belongeth vnto the firſt part. <hi>Beleeue me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me:</hi> this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecond. <hi>Beleeue you in God, beleeue alſo in me:</hi> and this vnto the third.</p>
               <p n="67">67 So then Faith in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6704:51"/>Chriſt, is not to know, or beleeue there is a Chriſt, nor yet to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue Chriſt, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt. The wicked beleeue there is a Chriſt, Hypocrites beleeue Chriſt, But the Elect only beleeue in Chriſt, that is, put their whole truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him.</p>
               <p n="68">68 Wherefore it is manifeſt that iuſtifying faith is not a bare know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge &amp; aſſent, but that the chiefeſt part thereof is Confidence, wherby the ſinner apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth and particularly appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6704:51"/>vnto himſelfe the promiſes of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="69">
                  <note place="margin">Note well.</note>69 Hence is that Theologicall Axiome: Some things are ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Faith, <hi>in reſpect of knowledge and aſſent;</hi> and ſome things <hi>in reſpect of Confidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="70">70 <hi>In reſpect of Aſſent,</hi> Faith hath for the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect thereof all the holy Scriptures, the Law &amp; the Goſpel, which faith firmely beleeueth to be moſt true.</p>
               <p n="71">
                  <note place="margin">The proper Obiect of Faith.</note>71 <hi>In reſpect of Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of faith, is the gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and mercy of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6704:52"/>in Chriſt the Redeemer, and offered by the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="72">
                  <note place="margin">Sole faith iuſtifieth.</note>72 Hereupon it is, that we conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that <hi>Sole Faith iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth;</hi> or, <hi>Faith only iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth:</hi> in which ſpeech the particle <hi>Sole</hi> or <hi>Only,</hi> determineth the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, but is not referred vnto the Subiect, that is, it declareth that this effect (Iuſtification) is attributed only to faith, and to no other appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending inſtrument or meanes.</p>
               <p n="73">73 Or, it ſheweth, that Faith is the only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6704:52"/>that apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="74">
                  <note place="margin">Note well.</note>74 As if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſay, <hi>The ſole eye ſeeth,</hi> or <hi>The eye only ſeeth:</hi> hee meaneth not, the ſole eie, or the eie only, that is, the ſolitary eye, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule, brain, eares, noſe, mouth, cheekes &amp;c. but the eye is the onely inſtrument of ſeeing, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther member of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p n="75">75 Wherefore the particle <hi>Sole</hi> or <hi>Onely,</hi> doth not exclude the grace &amp; mercy of God,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6704:53"/>the merit and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, nor the vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for all theſe are required in faith, which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel &amp; right vſe of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth and apprehendeth the grace of God and righteouſnes of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="76">76 Neither doth it exclude Workes &amp; the habite of Charitie, but only from the act of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying.</p>
               <p n="77">77 Hitherto of the <hi>Efficient Cauſe</hi> of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Now followeth the <hi>Materiall.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:6704:53"/>
                  <head>A PRAYER FOR <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>OH, ſweete Ieſus, moſt glorious and moſt gracious Lord. As the Harte brayeth after the riuers of water, ſo panteth my ſoule, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt mine eies look after thee, which art aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp to heauen to prepare a place for vs: Leaue not thy children deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. Prepare my going out and my comming in. Compaſſe me with thy mercy. Let thy holy Angell pitch his tent round about mee. Set a watch before my
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6704:54"/>mouth; Keepe the dore of my lips; turne mine eyes from vanity; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline not mine heart to euill, but prepare my ſoule to thy ſeruice, and deliuer mee from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euill worke. Shew mee the way, wherein I ſhould walke; let thy light goe before mee; teach me by thy word; giue me vnderſtanding by thy Spirit; frame my heart by thy grace. I am fleſh, quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. I haue neede of Faith, Hope and Loue; Let me not want the things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which I cannot
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6704:54"/>ſerue thee. Indue me with the grace of thy holy ſpirit, which is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to direct my ſoul, to informe my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and conforme my will. Worke in mee a certaine and ſtedfaſt faith in thee, aſſured Hope in thy promiſes, earneſt loue of thy truth and Goſpel, and ſincere affection towards thy Children. Thou haſt gone before me, O Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, make mee to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe mine example. Thou haſt begun, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou wilt not leaue off the worke thou haſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6704:55"/>in hand. See mee, O Lord, and not only ſo, but come to thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, come &amp; dwel with me, and all ſhall bee thine; onely make mee thine, ſweete Ieſus, as thou art mine. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Materiall Cauſe of Iuſtification.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſe of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He MATE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIAL cauſe of our Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuelie</hi> conſidered on Gods part, is the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of CHRIST
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6704:55"/>(<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.) called alſo, the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of God</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.) the <hi>gift of Righteouſnes</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17.) that <hi>Righteouſnes which is of God,</hi> (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.) the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of the Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 It is termed the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> becauſe Chriſt is the Efficient cauſe thereof: the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> becauſe GOD giueth the ſame freely, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth it vnto vs, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth it in his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Faith,</hi> becauſe we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6704:56"/>vnto it, or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it by Faith onely: and the <hi>Righteouſnes of the Goſpell,</hi> becauſe it is made manifeſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt hath two parts.</note>3 This <hi>Righteouſnes,</hi> being but one in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, hath two parts: 1. The <hi>Perfect fulfilling of the law of God.</hi> 2. The <hi>Voluntarie payment of the puniſhment for our diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Fulfilling of the Law; which is two-fold.</note>4 THe <hi>Perfect fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the law,</hi> is the full and exact conformitie of Chriſts humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and actions with the will of God reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6704:56"/>in both tables of the Decalogue.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And of this <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Conformity</hi> there are two members: 1. <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie.</hi> 2. <hi>Sanctitie or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 The <hi>Innocencie of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi>
                  </note> is that immunity or freedome from Sin, either Originall or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: For Chriſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had, nor commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any ſinne, for hee was both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued and borne without ſinne; and all his life time he neuer tranſgreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of God, either by fact, or word,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6704:57"/>or will, or cogitation, or by any euill concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.46.2. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> 5.21. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The <hi>Sanctitie of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sanctity.</hi>
                  </note> is that integritie or purity which Chriſt had from the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and retained in all his cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, words, deeds and deſires, vntill his verie death vpon the Croſſe. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.27.30. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.7.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Bearing of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>8 The <hi>Voluntary pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the puniſhment for our diſobedience,</hi> is the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6704:57"/>whole humiliation of Chriſt, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vntill his Glorification. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.7.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Galath.</hi> 3.13. <hi>&amp; alibi paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">Note well.</note>9 Of theſe two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and euery way ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Righteouſneſſe whereby wee are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: which both the <hi>Iuſtice of God,</hi> the <hi>Office of a Mediatour,</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Man</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily required.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>I. The Iuſtice of God.</hi> Becauſe the Iuſtice of GOD could not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6704:58"/>haue been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, but by perfect fulfilling the Law, and bearing the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which we had deſerued for the breach thereof.</p>
               <p n="11">11.<hi>II. The Office of a Mediatour:</hi> Becauſe our Suretie was reallie to pay the full price of our Redemption; both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely by doing, &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely by ſuffring thoſe things which we ought to haue performed.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>III. The Saluation of Man:</hi> Becauſe wee could neuer haue been redeemed otherwiſe, than by ſatisfying the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6704:58"/>law and iuſtice of God, by the perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and death of our Surety and Mediatour.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">The Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſe Paſſiuely taken.</note>13 The Materiall Cauſe of our Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Paſsiuely</hi> taken, are all the Elect (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33) being firſt in the ſtate of Nature vngodlie: (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.) <hi>God iuſtifieth the vngodly;</hi> and then in the ſtate of ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Grace beleeuing. (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.) <hi>The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> (is manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted) <hi>vnto all and vpon all that beleeue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 So much for the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6704:59"/>
                  <hi>Materiall Cauſe</hi> of our Iuſtification: Now of the <hi>Formall:</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A PRAYER FOR liuely ſenſe and aſſurance <hi>of Juſtification.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Moſt merciful Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhalt iudge al my words and workes, or rather anſwere both for mee and them, ſo direct, and order, and appoint my hart, my thought, to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue and labours to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, that as thou art the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> ſo I doe nothing but walke
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6704:59"/>in thy way, think of thy trueth, and aime at thy life; that by a godlie way, I may come to the heauenly truth, &amp; truth may leade mee to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. And becauſe fleſh and blood would turne thy Image to the image of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, my foes are thy foes, O Lord, let not thine enemies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt thee, to take me from thee: but let the aſſurance of my peace bee ſealed in my conſcience, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be left comfortleſſe. Make thy Word vnto me, like the Star which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6704:60"/>lead vnto thee: make thy benefits and graces, like the piller which brought vnto the land of promiſe. Kindle thy loue ſo in my heart, as in reſpect of thee and thy ſeruice, I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and vtterly deteſt whatſoeuer is againſt thee and thy truth, that I may alway find in my ſelf aſſured teſtimonies of the preſence of thy holy Spirit. O ſweete Sauiour, confirme my faith, which I feele of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes very weak and troubled with manie doubts; encreaſe it in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6704:60"/>me, O Lord, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy holy Spirit I may bee aſſured that thou haſt fully diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the puniſhment of my ſinnes. Cauſe me, O my God, to feele in my ſoule and conſcience, that thou art mine and all that thou haſt done; that I am grafted into thy bodie and made one with thee, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I am fellow-heire with thee of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Let me not only haue theſe words in my mouth, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy Spirit, let me feele the comfort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:6704:61"/>in my heart fully ſealed and ſetled in me; that I, feeling my ſelf inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before thy iudgment ſeate diſcharged, &amp; my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience towards thee appeaſed, may be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained loue toward thy heauenly Maieſtie, and towards my Brethren alſo for thy ſake, ſweete Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Formall Cauſe of Iuſtification.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall cauſe of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken.</note>THe FORMAL cauſe of Iuſtification Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6704:61"/>taken, is the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſnes, wherby the merits and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt are applied vnto vs, by force of that neere Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Chriſt with vs and ours with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 So that the <hi>Forme of Iuſtification</hi> doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together conſiſt in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: where in that Vnion which ariſeth betweene both termes, is indeede the forme, and conſiſteth rather in emanation than in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This Righteouſnes
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6704:62"/>is ours by <hi>Right of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and acceptation of Chriſts merits and obedience,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſeeing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſnes is of Grace not of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a benefit not real and habituall Poſſeſsion; &amp; Imputation not a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Qualitie inherent in vs.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Of Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>4 In this Imputation wee muſt conſider two things: 1. The <hi>Truth of it in it ſelfe.</hi> 2. The <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the truth of it in vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Of the <hi>Truth of it in it ſelfe</hi> there are two termes: 1. <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:6704:62"/>2. <hi>Imputation thereof.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts a Relation: for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath Chriſt his perfect Righteouſneſſe for any other end, but to impute it; neither doth hee impute anie thing, but his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes; neither is that Righteouſneſſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ours, but by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The <hi>Manner of the truth of it in vs,</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is circumſcribed by a two-fold reaſon. The <hi>firſt</hi> teacheth vs that we are Righteous, not in our ſelues, or by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6704:63"/>our own righteouſnes, but by the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt, which is made ours by Right of Donation, (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21) <hi>We are made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God in him.</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> teacheth vs that we haue Righteouſnes, as Chriſt hath our Sins.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">As Chriſt hath our Sinnes: ſo we haue his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>7 Chriſt hath our Sinnes, not ſubiectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inherent in himſelfe, but by imputation: ſo we haue Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, not ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely inherent in our ſelues, but by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Hereupon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6704:63"/>maketh that Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.) between Chriſt, whom <hi>God made Sinne for vs;</hi> and vs, who are made <hi>the Righteouſneſſe of God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 According vnto this Forme, the Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all men is one and the ſame, &amp; equall vnto all men; for one man cannot bee more iuſtified than another. Albeit in diuers me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Faith, the manner of it may well be ſaid to be diuers.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:6704:64"/>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">The forme of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken.</note>10 The <hi>Forme of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> Paſſiuely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in regarde of vs, is the Application of Faith: whereupon we are ſaid to bee iuſtified <hi>through Faith, of Faith,</hi> and <hi>by Faith:</hi> whereof we haue ſpoken in the <hi>Inſtrumentall Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 After the <hi>Formall,</hi> followeth the <hi>Finall</hi> cauſe of Iuſtification.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A THANKESGIVING for our Iuſtification inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt <hi>with Confeſſion and Prayer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Eternall GOD, in Chriſt Ieſus moſt gracious and mercifull,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6704:64"/>I thy poore ſeruant doe yeeld moſt poſſible and harty thankes vnto thy diuine Maieſtie, for all thy bleſſings and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, both ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall; eſpecially for the ſingular benefit of my Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable gift of eternall Saluation, purchaſed by the righteouſneſſe and deareſt life of thy belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Son. My lot is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in a pleaſant place; I am in honor, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it not. Hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one found ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in thy ſight? or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6704:65"/>haſt not thou paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer others, and choſen me? ô Lord, why ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou beſtow thy health and wealth, thy reſt and liberty vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, more then other? I can giue no reaſon for it, but that thou art mercifull. And if thou ſhouldeſt draw all backe againe, I haue nothing to ſay, but that thou art iuſt. Hath not thy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued libertie? Hath not thy <hi>Dauid</hi> deſerued reſt? Hath not thy <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> deſerued food? or hath not thy <hi>Iob</hi> deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued health, more then I
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6704:65"/>haue? <hi>Iob</hi> is ſicke, <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> pines without, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> is troubled on his bed, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> grones in the priſon: I haue their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; they do ſtand at reward. Why art thou ſo wel, my ſoul? Mercy, mercie. Why art thou ſo ill, my ſoule? ô Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. For notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe gracious and excellent benefits, yet haue I hitherto led my life ſo coldly in my profeſſion, &amp; wrought ſo contrarie vnto my vocation, in neglecting &amp; deſpiſing thy ſacred Commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6704:66"/>I haue more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked thee, to extend thy furious wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; recompence my leude deſert with the ſharpenes of thy reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging furie. But when I thinke vpon thy Son, all my feare is turned into ioy, becauſe his righteouſnes for me, is more then my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes againſt my ſelfe. O ſettle my faith in thy Beloued, &amp; it ſufficeth for all my iniquitie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie and infirmitie. Hee hath tolde vs, O Lord, and we beleeue it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6704:66"/>to bee true, that if wee aske thee any thing in his name, thou wilt graunt it vnto vs; now therfore in his name do I moſt earneſtly craue at thy hands, that thou wilt ſettle mee in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant forme of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that I may euer ſerue thee from this houre, with thoſe duties which the world, the fleſh &amp; the diuel would haue mee deferre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the point of death. Good Father, grant that I may loue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and pietie, with as great good will, as euer
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6704:67"/>I loued wickednes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanity; and that I may go before other in tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes towards thee, as farre as thou goeſt in mercy towards me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. O teach me to ſeek thee in al things, and all things in thee; euen for thy name ſake, for thy promiſe ſake, for thy Sons ſake, our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Finall Cauſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Finall cauſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification Actiuely taken.</note>THe FINAL Cauſe of Iuſtification Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6704:67"/>taken, is the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable temperature of his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercie: Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Of his Iustice:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would his Son ſhould make full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Of his Mercie:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would impute his Sonnes ſatisfaction vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">The Finall cauſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>4 The <hi>Finall Cauſe</hi> of Iuſtification Paſſiuelie taken, is that we might haue peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.) eternall life (<hi>Tit</hi> 3.7.) and bee euerlaſtingly glorified,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6704:68"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hitherto of the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of Iuſtification. Now of the <hi>Parts</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A PRAYER FOR eternall life.</head>
                  <p>OMnipotent and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, wee miſerable and wretched Sinners, do wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in this earth, as pilgrimes and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, readie to depart hence euery houre. We ſee daily with what vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and rage Death ſtriketh and choaketh
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6704:68"/>now one, now another for their grieuous ſins. But I giue thee moſt heartie thanks, O Lord, for thy infinite mercie towards me, that thou haſt not ſuffered me to be oppreſſed with pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable ignorance and heatheniſh blindnes, to periſh and die like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: but haſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly enlightened me with the pure light of thy Grace, and ſhewed vnto me the Cauſe of all calamities and of death, and manifeſted alſo the heauenly and ineſtimable comfort of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6704:69"/>eternal life, which doth wonderfullie recreate and cheere my heart. And whereas we feele, not without great grief with what crueltie and furie the wicked fiends, burning in hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, doe in theſe laſt dregs of the world oppugne mankind, and raiſe vp ſundrie dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſcandals and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther damnable enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt vs; we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of idleneſſe, of ſloth and weakenes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together corrupted &amp; defiled with carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, vnable to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6704:69"/>make reſiſtance: ô haue mercie vpon me, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto thy great mercie. Touch, moue and purifie my heart, that louing and fearing thee, I may ſeriouſlie and truly bewaile my great and ſo often ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated ſinnes; that I may ſtedfaſtly beleeue thy holy word, and leade the reſidue of my life in holines and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before thee. And ſeeing the greateſt part of mankinde, beeing drowned in Sodomiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call pleaſures, and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with Epicurean ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6704:70"/>doe not thinke or care for thee, not make any reckoning of eternall life; O Father giue me, and all the reſt of thy children, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute &amp; humble heart deſirous of eternall life and happineſſe. Guide vs by thy holie Spirit, that we may ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times meditate and ſpeake of thoſe euerlaſting &amp; ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall ioyes, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our owne hearts, and ſo reioyce, that like couragious Souldiers, wee may ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6704:70"/>cheerefully march after him through croſſes, tribulations, daungers and death it ſelfe, vntill wee ſafely ariue at thy heauenly palace, to bee partakers of that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glorie and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which thou haſt prepared for vs, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore to praiſe thee, O omnipotent and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God, for thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodnes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, who with the Son and Holy Ghoſt liueſt and raigneſt, one God, for euer and euer.<hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:6704:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Parts of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The parts of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion two.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He PARTS of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are two; <hi>Remiſsion of Sinnes,</hi> and <hi>Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Righteouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Note well.</note>2 But wee muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that theſe two parts are not diuers and different motions, but one really and in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which in reſpect of the diuerſitie of the termes whereabouts it is imploied hath diuers names.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In reſpect of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6704:71"/>
                  <hi>Term fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which</hi> it flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it is called <hi>Remiſsion of ſin,</hi> or <hi>Abſolution from ſinne,</hi> or <hi>Not-Imputation of ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 And in regard of the <hi>Terme vnto which</hi> it is applied, it is called, <hi>Imputation of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 For otherwiſe it is the very ſame motion whereby Sinne is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe procured: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.7.) where the Apoſtle termeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame thing, <hi>Imputation of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> which
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6704:72"/>Dauid called before (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.) <hi>Remiſsion of Sinnes. Euen as Dauid</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>declareth the bleſſedneſſe of man, vnto whom God imputeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe without workes, ſaying; Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, and whoſe ſins are couered.</hi> But wee will ſpeake of both theſe parts of Iuſtification ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerallie and apart.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Remiſſion of ſinnes.</note>6 <hi>Remiſsion of Sinnes,</hi> is the Abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of a Beleeuing man from the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of eternall death &amp; damnation for his ſin.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:6704:72"/>
               <p n="7">7 Or, a not-impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, not-puniſhing or couering of the Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſinne, and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him no ſinner.</p>
               <p n="8">8 In Remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin God taketh away three things: 1. <hi>Sin it ſelf,</hi> while hee doth not impute it. 2. <hi>The guilt of ſin.</hi> 3. <hi>The puniſhment due vnto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 The taking away of the two latter, to wit, of the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> neceſſarilie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the taking away of the former, namely <hi>Sinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 But this part of Iuſtification is denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6704:73"/>of Sinne, <hi>Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is the terme from which proceedeth the motion, and of which is firſt pronounced the ſentence of abſolution: albeit the ſentence bee pronounced alſo of the guilt and puniſhment, but in the ſecond place.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The ſentence of Remiſſion of ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once pronounced by God,<note place="margin">Note.</note> is neuer fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated or recalled: that is, Thoſe ſinnes that are once remitted and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, are neuer againe imputed. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18.21.22
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6704:73"/>
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.22. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18.19. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31.34.</p>
               <p n="12">12 If it bee demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:<note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether by Remiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes, the ſinne be ſo aboliſhed, that it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no more in man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">Anſwere. How ſinne is aboliſhed in Man.</note>13 I Anſwere: In <hi>Sin</hi> there are two things to bee conſidered, the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> and the <hi>Guilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 The <hi>Defect</hi> is not vtterly taken away, or aboliſhed out of the Subiect wherein it reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; but is daily dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by mortification of the old-man, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="15">15 For as long as we
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6704:74"/>carry this maſſe and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die about with vs, all Defects cannot bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed, ſeeing wee ſhall daily endure and feele the combate of the fleſh and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p n="16">16 But the <hi>Guilt</hi> is ſo aboliſhed and vtterly extinguiſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as that God abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmeth, that he will neuer reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber our ſins any more. (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.25.) <hi>I, euen I am hee that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away thine iniquities for mine owne ſake, and wil not remember thy ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 I will ſpeak more
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6704:74"/>Logically.<note place="margin">Note well.</note> 
                  <hi>Sinne</hi> is both in the Predicament of Qualitie, <hi>as it is a Vitioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> And alſo in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament of Relation; <hi>as it obligeth vnto dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18 Remiſſion of ſins, is not the deletion of the Vitioſitie, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe quality, as it is ſin: that is, it is not the vtter aboliſhing and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the Vitioſitie, that it remaineth not in the Beleeuer any more.</p>
               <p n="19">19 But ſinne is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, aboliſhed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, not marked by God, not ſeene, caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6704:75"/>his backe, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from vs, caſt into the bottome of the Sea &amp;c. not ſimplie but in two reſpects.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>First,</hi> in reſpect of the Obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or Imputation: Becauſe God doth not impute ſinne to them that are in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>Secondly,</hi> in reſpect of Dominion: Becauſe ſinne raigneth not in them that are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
               <p n="22">22 And thus our ſins are ſaid to bee couered, namely by the blood of Chriſt, leſt they ſhould
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6704:75"/>make vs guiltie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell damnation.</p>
               <p n="23">23 For otherwiſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> if <hi>Remiſsion of ſinne</hi> were a totall deletion and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exſtinction of al ſin, ſo that no ſin remained in the Regenerate; then it would follow that all that were iuſtified were wholy and altogether ſpirituall, without fleſh, that is, fleſhly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate againſt the fleſh, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall vnto the Angels, freed from all miſerie, trouble, diſeaſes, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bodily death. They
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6704:76"/>ſhould not rightly pray, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> Neither were that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> true (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.) <hi>If we ſay that we haue no ſin, we deceaue our ſelues and truth is not in vs.</hi> Nor that of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelfe (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17.) <hi>Sinne dwelleth in mee.</hi> Which were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and impious to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. For where the proper affections and effects of ſinne be, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionleſſe there is alſo ſinne it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="24">24 But I boldly ſay with the Apoſtle; that howſoeuer ſinne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6704:76"/>in the godly, yet <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Christ Ieſus. Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Thus farre of the firſt part of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Remiſsion of ſinnes:</hi> Now followeth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">
                  <note place="margin">11. Imputation of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</note>26 <hi>Imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,</hi> is the ſecond parte of Iuſtification, whereby God giueth, or aſcribeth CHRISTS Righteouſnes vnto vs freely, as if we our ſelues had performed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, whereby we attaine the Right of eternall life.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:6704:77"/>
               <p n="27">27 This is that <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of life</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18) and that <hi>Grace that raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by righteouſnes</hi> (of CHRIST imputed vnto vs) <hi>vnto eternal life. Rom.</hi> 5.21.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Of this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh vnto the Philippians (<hi>Philip.</hi> 3.7.8.9.) <hi>But the things that were vantage vnto mee, the ſame I counted loſſe for Christs ſake. Yea, doubtleſſe I think al things but loſſe for the excellent knowledge ſake of Christ Ieſus my Lord, for whom I haue counted all things loſſe, and do iudge them to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:6704:77"/>bee dung, that I might winne Christ. And might bee found in him, that is, not hauing mine own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, euen the righteouſneſſe which is of God through faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">
                  <note place="margin">What righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt is imputed vnto vs.</note>29 But that we may vnderſtand what <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt</hi> is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs: wee are to note that the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt is two-fold; <hi>Vncreated,</hi> &amp; <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſts Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not imputed.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30 His <hi>Vncreated Righteouſnes</hi> is his Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:6704:78"/>Iuſtice whereby he is God; and this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable: for the Eſſence of God cannot bee the Accident of Man.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <note place="margin">Chriſts created righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</note>31 His <hi>Created Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> is two-folde: 1. <hi>His Natiue and Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Sanctitie.</hi> 2. <hi>His Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> Or (which is the ſame in Effect) the <hi>Sanctitie of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the <hi>Sanctitie of his Actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32 Both theſe are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto vs: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Improperly,</hi> and the latter <hi>Properly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">
                  <note place="margin">1. His <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
                  </note>33 <hi>1.</hi> His <hi>Natiue and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:6704:78"/>habituall Sanctitie</hi> from the firſt moment of his Conception by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, was without meaſure, moſt perfect, moſt ſincere, moſt pure, free from al ſpot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</p>
               <p n="34">34 <hi>For ſuch an high Prieſt it became vs to haue which is holy, harmeleſſe, vndefiled, ſeparate from ſinnes</hi> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26.) Now Chriſt was not made thus by fulfilling the Law, but was ſo indeed from the firſt Article of his Conception.</p>
               <p n="35">35 And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the free benefit and gift of God.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:6704:79"/>
               <p n="36">36 Neither hath he by any his own deedes merited this great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to become our high Prieſt and Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, but was elected to that end by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free grace of God, <hi>before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p n="37">37 By this his holie Conception he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ours, who ought to haue been ſo concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the law of our firſt creation. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28.</p>
               <p n="38">38 Therefore was Chriſt conceiued holy without ſin for vs, that hee might deriue vnto
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:6704:79"/>vs, that which Adam could not doe; that he might ſupplie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of holineſſe in our conception, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our holie nature before God in himſelf: that ſo God might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our conception, as if wee had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued without ſin or blemiſh.</p>
               <p n="39">39 So alſo CHRIST was borne holy for our ſakes: for when wee ought to haue bin born holie, but could not, he abundantlie ſupplied that defect of holineſſe in our birth, and by his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:6704:80"/>holie natiuitie couered the impuritie of ours before the face of his Father.</p>
               <p n="40">40 Hee was borne holy for vs, becauſe he was not borne as other priuate men bee, but as the head of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Euen as Adam was not created a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, but as the head, the ſtocke and roote of his poſteritie.</p>
               <p n="41">
                  <note place="margin">Compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt with <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </note>Wherfore in this both of them are equal, that neither of them were conceiued of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſeede, nor had any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in earth.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:6704:80"/>
               <p n="42">42 Euen as Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was created holie though mutably, not onely for himſelf, but alſo for his whole ſeede: ſo Chriſt was borne holie &amp; that immutably, not onely for himſelf, but alſo for all his members.</p>
               <p n="43">43 Adam by reaſon of his fall could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Sanctitie of his creation (which was mutable, and ſo ſhould haue continued ſtil) with his ſeede: But Chriſt being ſtronger and more diuine than the firſt Adam, actually co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:6704:81"/>of his Natiuitie, which is immutable, with all his members and conſorts.</p>
               <p n="44">44 Wherefore the benefit that we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Note.</note> is far more excellent, then that which wee ſhould haue receiued by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="45">45 <hi>II. Chriſts Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Obedience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. His <hi>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                  </note> was the fulfilling of the will of his Father, &amp; ſatisfying his Iuſtice: aſwell <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely,</hi> by his volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuffering the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due vnto our ſins: (<hi>Philip.</hi> 2.8.) as alſo <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely,</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:6704:81"/>by perfect fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all the Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Diuine Law.</p>
               <p n="46">46 The Apoſtle faith (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19.) <hi>As by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners: So by the Obedience of one, ſhall many alſo be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="47">47 If the <hi>Diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Adam,</hi> whereby wee became ſinners, be the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion of the Law: then certainly the <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt,</hi> wherby we are made righteous, is the fulfilling of the Law.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:6704:82"/>
               <p n="48">48 And indeed a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cannot imagine any O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, but in reſpect of the Law whereunto it is performed.</p>
               <p n="49">49 Thus much of the <hi>Obedience of Christs hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature</hi> which is imputed vnto vs for righteouſnes.</p>
               <p n="50">50 Now that this Righteouſnes is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, appeareth by euident teſtimonies of Scripture. (<hi>Ro.</hi> 4.6.) <hi>Dauid declareth the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes of man, vnto whom God</hi> IMPVTETH <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes without workes.</hi> Alſo (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.) <hi>After
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:6704:82"/>he had receiued the ſigne of Circumciſion, as the ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith, which he had when he was vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, that he ſhould be the Father of them that beleeue, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing circumciſed, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes might be</hi> IMPV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED <hi>vnto them alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">
                  <note place="margin">Imputation two-fold.</note>51 Imputation is two-fold (as wee haue noted before) one <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> by debt; the other <hi>Euangelicall</hi> by grace.</p>
               <p n="52">52 <hi>Legall Imputation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Legall.</hi>
                  </note> is that whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, to whom the imputation is made.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:6704:83"/>(<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.) <hi>To him that worketh the wages is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by debt.</hi> Where there is a Relation betweene Wages and Workes; &amp; the wages is imputed for the worke.</p>
               <p n="53">53 Or, it is when God willeth and adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the reward to him that fulfilleth the Law in his owne perſon. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.</p>
               <p n="54">54 <hi>Euangelicall Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall.</hi>
                  </note> is that whoſe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation is not in him to whom the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made, but in the grace &amp; mercy of God who iuſtifieth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:6704:83"/>(<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.) <hi>To him that beleeueth in him that iustifieth the vngodly, his faith is counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi> Whereupon it is called the imputation of faith.</p>
               <p n="55">55 Or, it is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God accepteth the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt our Suer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as a payment for our ſinnes. In this ſenſe the word IMPVTE is repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ten times in the 4. chapter to the Rom.</p>
               <p n="56">56<note place="margin">Note well.</note> Neither is this Imputation a phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique ſpeculation, or idle conceipt: Seeing that euen as our ſinnes
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:6704:84"/>were really imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12) as is manifeſt by his Paſſion and Death the wages of ſinne. So is Chriſts Righteouſneſſe imputed vnto vs really, and with effect, that is, with the participation of diuine grace, and life eternall. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
               <p n="57">
                  <note place="margin">That we are not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by workes, or inherent Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>57 Hence appeareth that we are not iuſtified by inherent Iuſtice, by good workes, or infuſed habite of Charitie. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are iuſtified only by the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inherent in him, is
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:6704:84"/>by grace imputed vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="58">58 Againe, Inherent Iuſtice and Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are diſtinct giftes of God. (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.) <hi>Christ is made vnto vs of God, Wiſdome, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Sanctification.</hi> Alſo (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.) <hi>But yee are waſhed, but yee are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, But yee are iuſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="59">59 Alſo, the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe whereby a ſinner is iuſtified is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed without the law (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.) But inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Iuſtice and habite of Charitie is reuealed by the law: and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:6704:85"/>of Chriſt is the ſole Righteouſnes reuealed without the law.</p>
               <p n="60">60 Laſtlie, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith (<hi>Galat.</hi> 5.4.) <hi>Yee are aboliſhed from Chriſt, whoſouer are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the law, ye are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="61">
                  <note place="margin">Whoſoeuer will be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by workes cannot be ſaued.</note>61 Here it is euident that the doctrine of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by workes, is an error ouerturning the foundation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer obſtinately and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally maintaineth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaued.</p>
               <p n="62">62 For if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:6704:85"/>in their works, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe of their ſaluation, it is certaine, as the Apoſtle ſaith, (<hi>Galat.</hi> 5.2.) <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit them nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="63">63 If it be obiected:<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                  <hi>This is true of Ceremonial workes, but not of Morall workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="64">64 I anſwere:<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> Yea euen of <hi>Morall</hi> alſo: for the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the whole law (<hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</hi> 5.4.) <hi>Ye are aboliſhed from Chriſt, whoſoeuer are iuſtified by the law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="65">65 If any wil except:<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                  <hi>This is true of the works of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:6704:86"/>Nature, but not of workes of Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="66">66 I anſwere:<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Yea euen of <hi>Workes of Grace.</hi> And the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely teſtifieth, that by the Righteouſneſſe of a good conſcience we cannot be iuſtified. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>See alſo, Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="67">67 To adde any thing to the obedience of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Note well.</note> as a meritorious cauſe of our Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Saluation, is to make Chriſt vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
               <p n="68">68 For he muſt be a perfect Sauiour, or no
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:6704:86"/>Sauiour: hee admits neither partner nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie in the worke of our Redemption.</p>
               <p n="69">69 And the Grace of God admits no mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition with any thing that is of vs. Grace is no grace, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it bee euery way freely giuen.</p>
               <p n="70">70 Hitherto of the <hi>Partes of Iustification:</hi> Now of the <hi>Properties</hi> thereof.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:6704:87"/>
                  <head>A PATHETICAL Prayer againſt the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>of Satan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF I conſider my ſins paſt, why ſhould I liue to ſinne any more? If I lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e backe to my life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> why ſhould I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffer any more? I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſinned inough, but haue not yet ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red inough. Seize vpon my heart, O my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is thine, I haue giuen it vnto thee, that gaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy ſelfe wholly for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ee: take it, O Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; and look not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deformitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:6704:87"/>thou haſt bought it with thy deareſt blood; bathe it therein, ſcourge it, crucifie it, kill it and reuiue it, that being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, it may bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to remaine with thee. Oh, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſin! I haue liued long, yet but a while; I haue liued a while, yet very long; long for my Soule to ſtay ſo long from her Father, her Brother, and her one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Comforter. Meane while, I fight with my enemies, blinde, naked, weake, vnprouided:
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:6704:88"/>And who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I with mee? a Traytor; euen this Bodie of Sin. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, O Lord, thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant is but fleſh, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Satan, my enemie, conſider the World, my fained friend: whoſe part wilt thou take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelfe? Wilt thou giue the ſoule of thy Turtle doue to the beaſt? If thou wilt, thou canſt make mee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. Can my Lord forſake his owne? For the Spirit tels me, I am thine, and I beleeue it, ô Ieſus helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. Come therefore,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:6704:88"/>ſweet Ieſus, come now, Satan ſtandeth knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the doore of my youth, come quickly, and we will keepe him out. Auoide Sathan, crouch fleſh, be ſtill, my Soule: The Lord is on my ſide, I will not feare what any can doe vnto mee. There wanted a Tempter, and thou, O Lord, waſt the cauſe that hee was wanting; there wanted time and place, and thou waſt the cauſe that they wanted. The Tempter was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and there wanted neither time nor place,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:6704:89"/>but thou heldeſt mee backe, that I ſhould not conſent. Who hath trod vpon thy head, O Satan? Thou waſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but the Lord put thee downe; thou waſt masked, but the Lord diſcouered thee; thou waſt like an Angell, but the Lord tooke away thy vizard. Goe, take thy farewell, the net is broken, and I am eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Bleſſed bee thy name, my Lord, my Sauiour and my Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:6704:89"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Properties of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE PROPER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIES of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication conſiſt ſpecially in three things 1. That Iuſtification is <hi>Free.</hi> 2. That it is <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> 3. That it is <hi>Euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>I. Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is Free:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is free.</note> Becauſe Remiſſion of Sinnes is not giuen for any merits of man; but is a meere grace and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued mercie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for Chriſt his
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:6704:90"/>ſake alone.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For God findeth nothing in man whom he iuſtifieth but impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of ſin and extreme miſerie.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And the Scripture euery where affirmeth, that Chriſt onely is the author of all grace: and the whole hope of our ſaluation conſiſteth in his blood alone.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Without the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt there can be no iuſtification, for he hath purchaſed that Righteouſneſſe which GOD freely imputeth vnto vs.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:6704:90"/>
               <p n="6">6 They therfore that will be accounted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous without the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Atheiſts.</p>
               <p n="7">7 And they which dreame they are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, partly by grace, &amp; partly by their owne merits, are Pelagian Heretiques.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue they are iuſtified freely by the onely me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt, are true Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Againe, the Cauſe of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to wit, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt is free: wherefore Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:6704:91"/>it ſelfe muſt needs be free: for there cannot be more in the Effect, than there is in the Cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="10">10 If it be obiected:<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                  <hi>If GOD remitteth our ſins for the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, then doth hee not iuſtifie vs freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 I anſwere:<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Yes freely, in reſpect of our ſelues, that is, without any ſatisfaction of ours, but not without ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Again, if any will obiect: <hi>But he that iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in this manner, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth not freely; For what a
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:6704:91"/>man doth by another, hee may be ſaid to doe by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Therefore wee our ſelues haue paid the price by Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 I anſwere: God freelie giueth vnto vs this price, that is Chriſt our Satisfactor and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, which was not bought by vs (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.) <hi>So God loued the world, that he gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>II. Iuſtification is euery way perfect and moſt abſolute:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>II</hi> Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute.</note> for God doth not pardon one or two ſinnes onely, but forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all and euery ſin.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:6704:92"/>
               <p n="15">15 Neither doth he onely forgiue ſins that are alreadie committed and paſt; but remitteth the dailie falles of his children, if they repent. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.) <hi>The blood of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſin.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> (<hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.13.) God pardoneth <hi>all our treſpaſſes.</hi> See <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.22. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.12. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.19. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               <p n="16">16 If it be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:<note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bee abſolutely perfect and finiſhed in this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 I anſwer:<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> There
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:6704:92"/>are two ſorts of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which wee receiue of God in Chriſt: <hi>One of ſuch as bee not inherent in vs,</hi> as Election and Iuſtification. <hi>The other of ſuch as doe inhere,</hi> as Vocation, Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Both theſe kinds of Benefits haue this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that before the ful manifeſtation of Ieſus Chriſt, they cannot bee fully and perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared; I meane, neither Election, nor Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor Vocation, nor Glorification.</p>
               <p n="19">19 All theſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:6704:93"/>began to bee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the firſt manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and appearance of Chriſt (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.) <hi>Now is the Righteouſneſſe of God made manifeſt;</hi> but are not fully declared in this life; as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.2.) <hi>Now are we the ſonnes of God, but yet it doth not appeare what wee ſhall be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20 But they differ herein, that thoſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, are indeed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and really abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this life. (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.2.) <hi>Now wee are the ſonnes of God.</hi> So alſo,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:6704:93"/>Now wee are elected. Now we are iuſtified.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Thoſe Benefits which are inherent in vs, are not perfected in al their degrees, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inchoated or begun in this life.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Hence it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that iuſtification is indeed perfected &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued in this life, but not plainly manifeſted and declared.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Queſtion may be made:<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Chriſt will not Iuſtifie ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued heere, in the day of Iudgement: which if it be ſo, ſhall not Iuſtification be
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:6704:94"/>perfect then at length in that other life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. I Anſwere.<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> In that day of Iudgement, Chriſt wil not ſo much Iuſtify the Beleeuers; as declare, by their works, that they beleeued and were iuſtified euen in this life.</p>
               <p n="25">25 For ſo alſo the word, <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> may bee taken, and ſo <hi>Iames</hi> vſeth it, where he ſaith, that Man is iuſtified by his works. (<hi>Iac.</hi> 2.21.) <hi>He is iuſtified,</hi> that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be iuſtified.</p>
               <p n="26">Againe.<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Againe. It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: <hi>Seeing we daily
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:6704:94"/>pray vnto God for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of our ſins, that is, Iuſtification; how ſhall we ſay then, that Iuſtification is an vndiuidable act, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected euen at one and the ſame time in this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27 I Anſwere. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we pray for <hi>Remiſsion of ſinnes,</hi> wee pray not, as for a Benefit not yet gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs; but we pray for the increaſe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and application of the Benefit by faith, and for the encreaſe of our Faith.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Laſtly, it is obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <hi>If Iuſtification be the Sentence of life; and if that
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:6704:95"/>life ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be perfected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the comming of Chriſt: then certainely Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot be perfected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the laſt comming of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29 I Anſwere. It is one thing to <hi>perfect the Sentence of life,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to <hi>perfect life it ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30 The <hi>Sentence of life</hi> is perfected in this life; but <hi>Life it ſelfe</hi> is not perfected vntill the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="31">31 <hi>III.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtification is Euerlaſting:</hi> in as much as ſin ought not to bee imputed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:6704:95"/>are Iuſtified any more for euer.</p>
               <p n="32">32 For whom God hath once receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fauour, hauing blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out all their ſins and offences, thoſe doth he ſtill preſerue in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour as righteous.</p>
               <p n="33">33 So that ſuch can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vtterlie fall from grace and periſh by no manner of ſins, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and remaining par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For God will neuer remember thoſe ſins, to which the Regenerate are as yet ſubiect.</p>
               <p n="34">34 This the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:6704:96"/>expreſſely and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly affirmeth in many places (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.12.) <hi>I will remember thine iniquities no more.</hi> (<hi>Ierem.</hi> 31.34.) <hi>I will be merciful vnto their iniquities, and remember their ſinnes and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions no more. See Hebr.</hi> 8.12.</p>
               <p n="35">35 Theſe and ſuch like places of Scripture promiſe the Grace of God and forgiuenes of ſinnes, not for a day or two only; but ſignifie and affirme that it ſhall alwaies be of force, and continue while life la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, ſo that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:6704:96"/>of ſins is quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian and continuall al our life long.</p>
               <p n="36">36 Becauſe Chriſt hath made a ful and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſatisfaction for them once for all, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14.) And God is ſo iuſt that hee will not haue paiment and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for one thing twice. But is ſo well pleaſed with the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt, that hee requireth no other ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="37">37 Neither muſt we imagine, that therefore God is not diſpleaſed with ſinne in the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:6704:97"/>For the ſinnes euen of his owne dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt children doe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſe him; albeit he wil not puniſh them in his Saints, becauſe he hath puniſhed them in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="38">38 For GOD doth not ſo remit ſinnes as if he accounted ſinne no ſinne, or were not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at it: but becauſe he doth not impute them vnto vs, nor puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vs; but accounteth vs holy and righteous for the ſatisfaction of Chriſt apprehended by Faith.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:6704:97"/>
               <p n="39">39 Hitherto we haue ſpoken of the <hi>Properties</hi> of Iuſtification. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that wee ſpeake of the <hi>Effects</hi> thereof.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A PRAYER FOR Sanctification.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt glorious &amp; moſte gracious Lord, in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe infinite, in power almightie, in wiſedome wonderful, in iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t iuſt, in promiſe true, in mercie rich, patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſinners that call vpon thy name, &amp; ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, when they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: what ſhall I bee
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:6704:98"/>afraid to ask thee? Rule my paths, O Lord, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my heart. When I goe, let my gate bee ſtraight; when I runne, let me not fall, for I am a ſtranger vpon earth, &amp; vnderſtand not mine own way. I would walk at libertie, like thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Dauid.</hi> What ſaith my Lord? ſpeake now, for thy ſeruant heareth? <q>My Sonne, walke ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie after my word, for this is the plaine way, this is the ſure way: Heere thou ſhalt haue no lets, to ſtay thee; no encombrances, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:6704:98"/>thee. Goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtraight, and turne not: libertie is in thy way, and Life is in the end. But if thou looke back, or ſtay, or turne to the right hand, or to the left; then thou falleſt into a hedge of thornes, nets &amp; ſnares take hold vpon thee. A double heart, and a man that goeth two waies ſhall not proſper, I am wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of the ſimple and open hearted. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> is troubled with much buſines, but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> hath all things at my feete: therefore haue I
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:6704:99"/>ſeparated thee (if thou wilt) becauſe thou canſt not ſerue two maſters.</q> It is true, Lord, for I am neuer diſtracted in minde, but when I am carefull about manie things: For ſo long as thou art with me, I am thine; but when I bring in ſin, then am I ſtraight diſpoſſeſſed of my ſoul. If I loue any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee, it vpbraideth me: if I ſpeake, or doe any thing without thy counſaile, ſtraight I am trapt in ſome errour, wearie of my ſelfe and vnapt for thee. It is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:6704:99"/>to thinke how my heart is hardened, my vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, my teares dried vp, when thou turneſt thy face but from mee, and Sin preuaileth againſt mee. Had I the ſpirit to diſcerne euery thing at his value, I ſhould loue God before all, which is beſt of all, and Man after GOD, which is next to GOD. How is my Soule troubled for this? and my heart rent in twaine, vntil my fleſh conſent, and all my me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers agree together, to chuſe that which hee
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:6704:100"/>hath commanded, and to forgo that which he hath forbidden? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was afflicted, I went aſtray, like a thing vntamed: it is good for me that I haue bin tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that I may learne thy Statutes. Saue me now, O Lord, I pray thee. Now, Lord, I pray thee giue mee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. I haue ſinned, I am ſorie, forgiue mee. Away from me, all you that worke vanitie, for the Lord is my GOD; if I regard wickedneſſe in my heart, he will not heare me. O thou eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:6704:100"/>Goodneſſe, which art good to all, which guideſt thoſe that ſeeke thee, which enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thoſe that ſee thee, and which ſaueſt thoſe that loue thee; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due mee with thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and holie Spirit, which may ſubdue all my carnall affections; which may rectifie my reaſon, regenerate my will, and purifie my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that at all times, when thou ſhalt call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, I may be readie with <hi>Dauid</hi> to anſwer, <hi>Loe I come: Praiſed bee God.</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:6704:101"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Effects of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Effects of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Effects</hi> of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are Peace of Conſcience (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.) Acceſſe vnto God (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12.) Adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the ſonnes of God (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.16.17. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.26. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12.) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11.) Externall life &amp;c. (<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22.23.) al which may bee reduced vnto this one, <hi>Glorification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Of Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>2 <hi>Glorification,</hi> is the
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:6704:101"/>execution of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of life pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God in Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In Glorification we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Application; the <hi>one of God;</hi> the <hi>other of ſuch as are to be Glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>Application of God,</hi> is that whereby God ioineth Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as the Head to the reſt of the body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he alſo giueth vs his holy Spirit.</p>
               <p n="5">5 In this Application God ioineth Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, being firſt <hi>Dead,</hi> for mortification of our
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:6704:102"/>fleſh or old man; ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>quickned or raiſed from Death,</hi> for viuification of our Spirit or new man.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The <hi>Application of ſuch as are to be Glorified,</hi> is that whereby we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Chriſt being ioyned vnto vs in his <hi>Death</hi> and in his <hi>Life,</hi> by faith, wrought by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7 And in this Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, both of God &amp; of our ſelues, whereby Chriſt is ioyned vnto vs, as Head vnto the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is manifeſtly depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended our Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:6704:102"/>or renewing.</p>
               <p n="8">8 For by the ſame act (as it were) and at the ſame inſtance, as ſoone as euer Chriſt is ioined vnto vs, as Head, we are preſentlie made his Members, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or new birth.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note>9 Glorificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: <hi>Inchoatiue Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3.) &amp; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatiue Glorification. Matth.</hi> 19.28.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Inchoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</hi>
                  </note>10 <hi>Inchoatiue Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> is that whereby (we being vnited vnto Chriſt) our corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, euen in this life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:6704:103"/>to be renewed by the holy Ghoſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the Image of God. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.23.24.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The ſame is alſo termed, <hi>Regeneration</hi> &amp; <hi>Sanctification.</hi> But <hi>Paul</hi> ſimplie calleth it, <hi>Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.) that is, a glorious renewing of our Nature, an aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of our corrupt Nature, and making of vs fit for eternall Glory.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <note place="margin">Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath two parts.</note>12 Of this Inchoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Glorificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, there are two parts, 1. <hi>Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or killing <hi>of the Olde
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:6704:103"/>Man,</hi> that is, Hatred of ſinne. 2. <hi>Viuification</hi> or quickening <hi>of the New Man,</hi> that is, Loue of Righteouſnes.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">Old Man what.</note>13 By <hi>Olde Man,</hi> I meane, the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, aſwel ſoule as body, addicted vnto ſinne and death: or the vnregenerated part and corrupt nature of man; termed alſo the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man,</hi> &amp; <hi>Fleſh</hi> (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6.) alſo the <hi>Body of ſinne</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6.) &amp; <hi>the ſinfull body of fleſh, Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>Mortification of the Olde-Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                  </note> is that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:6704:104"/>wherby the holy Ghoſt by litle and litle wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs a deteſtation and hatred of ſinne, and exſtinguiſheth the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in vs, that it might not bring foorth moſt bitter fruits to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <note place="margin">New Man what?</note>15 By <hi>New-Man,</hi> is meant the Nature of man, that beginneth to ceaſe from ſinne, or that part of man, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and reſtored according vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Image of God: termed alſo, the <hi>Inward man</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22.) and the <hi>hidden man
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:6704:104"/>of the heart</hi> (1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.) alſo <hi>Spirit, Ioh.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p n="16">The <hi>Viuification of the New-Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Viuifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> is when we are raiſed vp into a new and ſpirituall life (hauing the habite of Charitie infuſed into vs) that wee might liue vnto righteouſnes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4.5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Againe, Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is as well of the <hi>Soule,</hi> as of the <hi>Bodie,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23.1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <note place="margin">Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soule.</note>18 <hi>Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Soule,</hi> is that whereby the faculties of the ſoul are renewed.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Of the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:6704:105"/>of the Soule there are two parts, 1. <hi>Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> 2. <hi>The gift of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20 For as there are two parts of the Soule, the <hi>Vnderstanding</hi> and the <hi>Will:</hi> ſo in both Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation is required. Illumination is of the Vnderſtanding (<hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.10.) and Repentance of the Will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>Illumination,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> is that wherby God diſpelleth the naturall darkeneſſe, blindnes &amp; ignorance of our minds, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth it with the ſauing knowledge of
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:6704:105"/>himſelfe (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.) which is Eternal Life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3.</p>
               <p n="22">22 It is alſo termed, <note place="margin">Note.</note> the <hi>Vnction,</hi> or <hi>anoynting of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.20. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.</p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>The gift of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
                  </note> is that whereby our Will is renewed &amp; willeth not euill any more, but only good, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.18. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.5.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22.23.24. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <note place="margin">Repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath two parts.</note>24 Repentance hath two parts, 1. <hi>Auerſion
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:6704:106"/>from the Diuell and all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> 2. <hi>Conuerſion vnto God &amp; all good, Pſ.</hi> 34.15. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 37.27. <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22.23.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9.10. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11.</p>
               <p n="25">25 So much for the <hi>Regeneration of the Soule:</hi> Now followeth the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation of the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">
                  <note place="margin">Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body.</note>26 <hi>Regeneration of the Body,</hi> is that wherby the Body is made obedient vnto the renewed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo that it attempteth nothing, but what is conformable vnto the will of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:6704:106"/>
               <p n="27">27 Of the Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body, there are two parts. 1. <hi>Bridling of the Affections.</hi> 2. <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of the moueable Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28 The <hi>Bridling of the Affections,</hi> is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of them vnto the regenerated or renued Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="29">29 The <hi>Gouerning of the moueable Members,</hi> is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the Members are ſo guided, that they commit nothing being ruled by diſordred paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or euill luſt, againſt the conſent of the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated Minde &amp; Will.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:6704:107"/>
               <p n="30">30 The infallible to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and certaine marke of Regeneration, is a Holy and iuſt life.</p>
               <p n="31">31 And thus much of <hi>Inchoatiue Glorification:</hi> It followeth to ſpeake of that which is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32 <hi>Conſummatiue Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue.</hi>
                  </note> is that moſt perfect and euery way happie fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of GOD, which all the Elect ſhall eternally enioy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this life, where they ſhall ſee God face to face, and know, as they are knowne, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing full fellowſhippe
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:6704:107"/>with IESVS CHRIST, and raigning with him for euer. Wherof (God willing) according to our mediocritie, wee purpoſe to entreate in a ſeuerall Treatiſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A THANKS GIVING for our Redemption, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>with Prayer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHat? Can Man ſay, that he hath any thing, that he hath not receiued? Who hath elected? who hath created? who hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? who hath iuſtified? who hath ſanctified?
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:6704:108"/>who hath preſerued you from day to day, O Soule, O Bodie? The Lorde hath made all things for you, and you for himſelfe. O moſt gracious &amp; louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which art loued for thy goodneſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, reioyced in for thy happineſſe, praiſed for thy merits, and prayed vnto for thy mercies! I acknowledge I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worthilie praiſe thee, nor thanke thee, as I ought: my tongue faultreth, my heart fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, my Spirit langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:6704:108"/>I want words to expreſſe and powre out my mind; I want a mind to conceiue and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend thy benefits. My words are ſhort of my vnderſtanding; and my vnderſtanding farre vnder the dignitie of thy deſerts. By thy loue I was elected, by thy goodnes I was created, by thy Spirit I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by thy mercy I was iuſtified, by thy grace I was ſanctified, and by thy power I am preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. When I had no being thou diddeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect me, when I was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:6704:109"/>thing thou didſt create me, when I was worſe than nothing thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt call mee, when I was thine enemie thou didſt iuſtifie me, when I was habitually euill thou didſt ſanctifie me, and now being vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for all thy mercies thou doeſt preſerue me ſtill. O exceeding bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, proceeding from vnſpeakable goodnes! O ineſtimable mercie flowing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurpaſſing loue! What thankes? what praiſe ſhall I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto thee for this thy vndeſerued kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:6704:109"/>If I had the tongue and knowledge of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, yet could I not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently laud thee, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible goodnes infinitly exceedeth all bounds both of vtterance and vnderſtanding? Well therefore may I admire thy mercies in ſilence, but ſpeake of them as is meet, I cannot, I am not able. Yet, O ſweete Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, let mee not bee vnthankfully ſilent for theſe thy benefits, but teach my heart how with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it ſhould thinke of thee; giue my
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:6704:110"/>tongue ſome power to liſpe and ſtammer out thy praiſes, ſeeing it can not ſpeake and powre them foorth with ſuch volubilitie &amp; freedome it ought, and grant that in ſome meaſure I may loue thee, though not ſo much as thou deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, yet ſo much as I am able to performe. O good Lord, diddeſt not thou elect mee, that I ſhould loue thee? didſt not thou create me, that I ſhuld loue thee? didſt not thou call me, that I ſhould loue thee? didſt not thou iuſtifie mee,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:6704:110"/>that I ſhould loue thee? didſt not thou ſanctifie mee, that I ſhould loue thee? &amp; doeſt not thou ſtill preſerue me, that I ſhould loue thee? It is true, Lord, that I haue not deſerued what I craue; but wilt thou therefore loſe thy due? for I can neither thank, nor praiſe, nor think of thee as I ought, except I loue thee. Accept therfore, O bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, accept of my baſe and bare loue. I haue no other thing to giue thee for all thy mercies, but euen my
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:6704:111"/>loue, my ſelf, which yet is alreadie thine owne: But I am ſo ſoiled and defiled with ſinne, that it is a point of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie fauour, if in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion thou wilt now accept, that which in right hath been alwaies thine. But if I be full of wickedneſſe, art thou therefore not full of goodnes? If I be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie for my impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, art thou therefore not praiſe-worthie for thy mercie? If I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my iniquitie, wilt thou therfore deny thy pitie? I am a ſinner, but
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:6704:111"/>yet thy creature. I am a Sinner, but yet redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with thy precious blood. I am a Sinner, but remember, Lord, thou cameſt into the world to ſaue Sinners, whereof I am chiefe. Thou cameſt to ſaue Sinners, and wilt thou reiect me? Thou cameſt to ſeeke that which was loſt, &amp; wilt thou ſee me periſh? Thou cameſt to ſeeke thoſe which ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wilt thou refuſe them which crie after thee? Thou cameſt to call Sinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and wilt thou not
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:6704:112"/>heare them when they doe repent? Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſweete Ieſus, I am a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I am loſt, I haue ſtraied, I repent, I am he for whoſe ſake thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into the world: help me now, or tell me who ſhall helpe mee? Saue thy ſeruant, or tell me who ſhall ſaue me? I know, Lord, I know there is no Redeemer, there is no Sauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee. If thou refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt a poore captiue, that condemneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and calleth vpon thee; ô Redeemer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt thou then redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med?
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:6704:112"/>If that ſinner ſhall be drowned in hell, that deſpaireth in himſelfe, and truſteth in thee; O Sauiour who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilt thou then ſaue? Haue mercy therefore vpon mee, O Sauiour, O Redeemer, aſſwage my grief, heale my diſeaſes, purge my ſinnes. Thou that haſt called me, before I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon thee, hearken now vnto my prayer, and let my crie come vnto thee, euen for thy mercies ſake, for thy loues ſake, for thy own ſake, ſweete Ieſus. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:6704:113"/>
                  <head>A MORNING PRAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for a priuate Familie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is vaine to riſe early, and to lye downe late, except the Lord be with vs: ſo vaine a thing is Man. Therefore wee will not attempt any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue taken cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile and ſtrength from the Lord, that hee may deliuer vs from euery euill worke. If wee aske that thing which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, deny our ignor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ace; If wee aske that thing which is good, O Lord, remember thy promiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WE ſlept and roſe againe, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:6704:113"/>for thou diddeſt watch for vs that wee might take our reſt. The heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s declare thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the earth is full of thy goodneſſe. Yet haſt thou not dealt ſo with all Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as thou haſt loued Sion thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hill; a corner of the world farre ſeparated from the Serpent, and fenced from the wilde beaſt. Yet who conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that our perill is gone into other lands, becauſe their Gods be not like vnto our God? Wee haue ſeene thy workes, &amp; yet we proue
<pb facs="tcp:6704:114"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>ue thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> we ſee thy w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Thou haſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> vs from the Turke, and deliuered vs from the Pope: &amp; why haſt thou ſeparated vs from them, but that we ſhould bee ioyned to thee? euen a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture come out of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to light, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> working of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. O bind our harts with thy feare, that wee part not from thy loue! For our ſelues and for our Brethren, wee are proſtrate heere before thee, ô Prince moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent.
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:6704:114"/>For the name of thy only Son, one drop of mercy to coole this fire of ſinne. Nothing, good Lord, to change thy mercy? yet the whelpes doe eate the crummes that fall from their maſters table. Firſt wee yeelde thee hartie thankes for all at once. Next, we humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral quittance which thy Son hath ſealed for our ſinnes. Then, for all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we pray thee let vs not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which wee cannot ſerue thee. Plant in our
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:6704:115"/>hearts true feare of thy name, obedience to our Prince, and loue to our Neighbours. Giue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, good Father, to our prayers: graunt vs true humilitie in proſperity, perfect patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in aduer ſitie, peace in Chriſt, &amp; ioy in the holy Ghoſt. This is our deſire, to liue godly, righteouſly and ſoberly: ſo bleſſe vs and keepe vs, good Father, vnto the end of our liues. Turne vs, O God of our ſaluation, graunt that we may grow from ſtrength to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, that thy Church Militant
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:6704:115"/>may be like thy Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in heauenly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and all Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints. Send thy labourers into thy vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, purge thy Church of idle &amp; ignorant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; write thy lawes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tables of our harts, &amp; powre thy grace vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearers. Bleſſe them which bleſſe vs; look vpon this Realme in thy mercy. Preſerue our King; let not the eye of Great Britaine loſe his ſight. Be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our friends [and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents] according vnto
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:6704:116"/>the fleſh: comfort thine afflicted Saints. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the power of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, ſend thy feare amongſt them, make their time ſhort, defend thine owne cauſe: As thou art ſanctified in vs before them, ſo be thou magnified in them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs; that al the world may turne &amp; ſay, Great art thou, O Lord God of the Chriſtians, and there is none beſides thee mightie, iuſt and mercifull, rewarding righteouſnes, &amp; reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging iniquitie, the ſame now, and euer, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:6704:116"/>where. Graunt theſe things, ô heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; whatſoeuer elſe thou knoweſt to bee needfull for vs, euen for his ſake, who died for ſin and ſinned not; in whoſe name we farther pray vnto thee, as hee hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>O our Father which art in heauen &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God the Father which hath made vs, bleſſe vs; God the Sonne, which hath redeemed vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs; God the holy Ghost, which hath ſanctified vs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our ſaith, to the end, and in the end. Oh God, Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghost ſaue vs,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:6704:117"/>
                  <head>AN EVENING Prayer for a priuate Familie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wee haue ſinned: wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. O Father haue mercy vpon vs. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord God, which haſt created vs of nothing, which haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs from Death and damnation, if wee doe not wilfully runne vnto it; that haſt been good and gracious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in continuing thy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall bleſſings both at home &amp; in the field, euen as thou ſeeſt moſt
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:6704:117"/>expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for our eſtate, and haſt drawne out the thred of our life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this preſent time. Theſe are thy greate mercies, O Lord, giuen vnto vs freely without any deſeruing of ours. And for all theſe thou requireſt nothing elſe of vs, but that we know thee, and acknowledge thee to bee the giuer thereof, and to obey thee, and to walk in the paths of thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, that ſo wee might become thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; be partakers of thine euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:6704:118"/>dome, and raigne with thee for euer. O Lord, we confeſſe againſt our ſelues our wonderfull fooliſhnes &amp; vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes: For wee haue, euen as much as in vs lieth, ſtopped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreame of thy mercies, that they ſhould not come neere vs, wee haue not hearkened vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice of thy word, neither tooke wee any delight in keeping thy lawes &amp; thy ſtatutes: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou haddeſt lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before this cut vs ſhort, as thou haſt done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that ſuddenly
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:6704:118"/>and fearfully, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned vs to appeare, &amp; to hold vp our hands at the barre, before thy iudgement ſeate, and haue the fearefull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſpeedily gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen foorth againſt vs: who is there could ſay, <hi>What doeſt thou?</hi> Nay our owne conſciences would acquite thee, &amp; ſay thou haſt done iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For ſeeing thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledſt after vs, and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to heare thee, it was good reaſon wee ſhould crie and find no mercie. But, O Lord, as
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:6704:119"/>our ſinnes are mightie, and cannot bee num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, ſo thy mercie far exceedeth and ſtriueth againſt our lewdneſſe. Thou haſt ſpared vs long, and giuen vs a large time of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Thou haſt driuen off thy vengeance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to daye, waiting and watching for our tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againe vnto thee. Thou haſt called vs by ſignes in Heauen, by ſhaking the earth, by drowning vs with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by threatning vs warre, ſamine and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, beſides the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:6704:119"/>threatnings of thy word. Euen ſo, O Lord, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> theſe haue their working in our hearts together with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in time to repent, &amp; turne from our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked waies, to abuſe thy patience no longer, but euen with all our heart to turne vnto thee, if ſo we may be ſaued in the day of thy wrath. So work thou in vs, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, that wee delay no longer to aske counſaile at thee, and thy word, what wee ought to doe, what we ought not to doe, and
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:6704:120"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="217" facs="tcp:6704:120"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="218" facs="tcp:6704:121"/>how wee may liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly in proſperitie, and how wee may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in ſickneſſe and aduerſitie, that we may goe out of our ſelues and looke for all things at thy goodneſſe, that wee may truſt no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to theſe tranſitorie things, but wholly relie vpon thee. Bleſſe, O Lord, we beſeech thee thy whole vniuerſall Church, the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, the Queene and Prince, the priuie Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, Magiſtrates and Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this land; ſpecially haue mercie
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:6704:121"/>as vpon this familie and euery member of the ſame, ſo alſo vpon all our friends [and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents] according vnto the fleſh, and continue thy Goſpel vnto vs and to our poſteritie after vs, euen for thy deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe name we further pray vnto thee as hee hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>O our Father which art in heauen &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let thy mighty hand, and out ſtretched arme, O Lord, be ſtill our defence, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and louing kindneſſe in Ieſus Christ thy deare Son
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:6704:122"/>our ſaluation, thy true and holie word our inſtruction, thy grace and holie Spirit our comfort and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnto the end and in the end. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord bleſſe vs and ſaue vs, the Lord make his face to ſhine vpon vs, and be mercifull vnto vs; The Lord turne his fauourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance toward vs, and this night and euermore vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to ſend vs thy euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting peace. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the loue of God, and the fellowſhip of the holy Ghoſt be with vs all euermore. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="221" facs="tcp:6704:122"/>
                  <head>A PRAYER TO BE ſaid for a ſicke man: or by the <hi>ſick man himſelfe, altring but the perſon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Moſt merciful God &amp; gracious Father, which through corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſeaſes putteſt vs in minde of our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and alſo calleſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that vnto thee belongeth health and ſaluation, thou raiſeſt vp and caſteſt downe, thou makeſt ſicke and makeſt whole, thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreſt to life and takeſt away by death: We,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:6704:123"/>thy vnworthy ſeruants, doe here preſent our ſelues before thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Maieſtie, in the name and mediation of thy deareſt Son Ieſus Chriſt, humbly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee in the behalfe of this thy poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that lieth viſited vnder thy hand, that thou wouldeſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke him in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, nor chaſten him in thy wrath. Haue mercy on him, O Lord, for he is weake, O Lord heale him, for his bones are vexed. Wee know, O Lord, and himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:6704:123"/>that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame mould that we are, and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame loines, he muſt needes be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſame cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of originall ſin that wee are, and alſo ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame death and damnation. But, O gracious &amp; louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee beſeech thee, ſeale in his heart by thy holy Spirit the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all his ſinnes, lay not to his charge what he hath ſaid or done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe throughout the whole courſe of his life, but reare him vp in
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:6704:124"/>hope, and let thy holy Spirit lead him vnto the throne of thy mercy. Let the ſweet feeling &amp; taſte of a liuely faith, diſtaſt al corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that are in him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſinfull body and ſoule may be cleered and waſhed by the blood of thy Son. And if this his ſickneſſe be not vnto the death, may it pleaſe thee, O Lord, to help him, vpon the bed of his ſorrow: turne the whole palate of his weaknes into ioy. Heale him &amp; he ſhal be whole, ſaue thou him &amp; he ſhall bee ſaued. Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:6704:124"/>him from the pit of corruption; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue will not acknowledge thee nor death confeſſe thee; but the liuing, we ſay, the liuing will extol thee for euermore. But if it be more expedient for him to die then to liue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deale with him according to thy wil, O Lord, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his ſoul to be receiued in peace, which we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend into thy hands that haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed it. Take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him all the feare &amp; ſorrowes of death, and giue him a through ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth againſt all the aſſaults of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:6704:125"/>that he may haue a perfect victory. Rayſe the ſiege of his ſpiritual enemies that are round about him, and let thy gracious defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection be ouer him to keep him faſt to thee &amp; thy truth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end. And, good Lord, ſhew this mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that the knowledge of thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which he hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſince thou haſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him thereby, may now ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him in ſteed, &amp; releeue his faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the knowledge of thee and of himſelfe, he may haue true repentance,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:6704:125"/>that he may yeeld vnto thee true obedience; &amp; be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull, whatſoeuer thou ſhalt do vnto him, &amp; in regard of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and of thoſe ioyes which thou haſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for him, he may wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forſake this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent euil world, &amp; come vnto thee fighting a good fight, &amp; fighting with ioy, and ſo recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an vncorruptible crowne, may liue with thee for euer and euer. And now, good Father, for vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are about him, teach vs to know our owne weaknes, that we
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:6704:126"/>may worthily thinke of the frailties of our vaine and tranſitory life, that wee may prepare our ſelues vnto death, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be in a readines looking vp to that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdom which thou haſt purchaſed for vs. Grant theſe things we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech thee, both for him and for vs, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake our only Sauiour and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reuel. 7.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amen.</hi> Praiſe, and Glory, and VViſdome, and Thankes, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and Power, &amp; Might, be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
